<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Wisdome and innocence, or prudence and simplicity in the examples of the serpent and the dove, propounded to our imitation. By Tho. Vane doctor in divinity and physick.</title>
            <author>Vane, Thomas, fl. 1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 95 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96039</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V89</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1406_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209492</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868369</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868369</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169921</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96039)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169921)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 181:E1406[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Wisdome and innocence, or prudence and simplicity in the examples of the serpent and the dove, propounded to our imitation. By Tho. Vane doctor in divinity and physick.</title>
                  <author>Vane, Thomas, fl. 1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 182 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Crook, and J. Baker, and are to be sold at the sign of the Ship in St. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 1.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Symbolism in the Bible --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Virtues --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169921:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>WISDOME AND INNOCENCE, OR PRUDENCE And SIMPLICITY, In the examples of The SERPENT And the DOVE, Propounded to our imitation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Tho. Vane <hi>Doctor in Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Phyſick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON. Printed for <hi>J.Crook,</hi> and <hi>J. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> and are to be Sold at the ſign of the Ship in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:169921:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169921:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, <hi>MILDMAY,</hi> Earl of <hi>Weſtmorland,</hi> Baron <hi>Deſpencer</hi> and <hi>Burwaſh,</hi> &amp;.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou who have bin my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, have moſt right to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage
<pb facs="tcp:169921:3"/> of any thing that is mine. Hence it is, that I preſume to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent this unto your Lordſhip; both to confeſs my obligation, &amp; expreſs my gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude. Which although it be in a ſmall propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet ſeeing
<pb facs="tcp:169921:3"/> men doe not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe their dues, though never ſo little; nor cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous men ſleight gratitude, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though offered in never ſo ſmall a ſervice; if it hold any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion with the ability, or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of the
<pb facs="tcp:169921:4"/> offerer; I hope that this, under theſe conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſhall not be rejected by your Lordſhip, being tendred by him, who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours, Moſt humble, obliged, and grateful Servant, THO. VANE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169921:4"/>
            <head>Of the Prudence of the Serpent, and Simplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Dove.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UR Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> ſending forth his Apoſtles to preach unto the world, and knowing well what enmitie God put from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining betwixt the Seed of the Woman, and the Serpent, and that from thence the children of this world ſhould perſecute the children of God; like a wiſe Captain, diſcovers unto them
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169921:5"/> the ſtrength and power of their Enemies, and withall furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them with armes fit for their defence. He tells them, in the 10. chapter of S. <hi>Matthews</hi> Goſpell, that he came not to ſend peace, but the ſword; that they muſt not look (like <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>) to be lulled aſleep in the lap of <hi>Dalila,</hi> but like <hi>Jona</hi> to be caſt into the ſea, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe the ſtorm; to be ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up by the whales, the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous monſters of the earth; to be arraigned before the ſeats of juſtice; to be chaſed from citty to city, yea to have thoſe in whoſe names are included the greateſt notes of friendſhip, to be as farr from it in exerciſe, as they are neer it in title; and to have for a mans enemies, thoſe of his own howſhold. In ſum, to find nothing in the world, but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169921:5"/> a world of wolf-turn'd men as it is in the 16. verſe of the ſaid chapter; <hi>Behold, I ſend you forth as ſheep in the midſt of wolves:</hi> whence followeth this inſtruction, <hi>Be yee therefore prudent as ſerpents, and ſimple as doves.</hi> Chriſt alſo came (as he ſaith) <hi>to ſeek and to ſave that which was loſt;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke. 19.10.</note> and that which was loſt in <hi>Adam</hi> being the wiſdome of the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the innocence of the will, he propounds unto us theſe two, as patterns to renew them thereby, no beaſt being ſo wiſe as the Serpent,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.1.</note> as the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, who was therefore (in the braſen Serpent ſet up in the wilderneſs) a type of Chriſt, who is the wiſdome of the father; nor any ſo ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and innocent as the Dove, which is therefore the Emblem
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169921:6"/> of the Holy Ghoſt, who is the fathers love.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bee prudent,</hi> to encounter with the policies of the world; <hi>be ſimple,</hi> and free from purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the pleaſures of the world. <hi>Be prudent, as ſerpents,</hi> to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the worlds ſnares; <hi>be ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as doves,</hi> to cover their ſins. <hi>Be prudent, as ſerpents,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline the worlds injuries; <hi>be ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as doves,</hi> in not revenging the injuries of the world. Be not altogether as Doves, left yee fall into others dangers; be not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together as Serpents, left yee endanger others: for as pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence joyned with malice, is not more prudence than wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, ſo ſimplicity joyned with ignorance, is not ſo much ſimplicity as folly. In ſimplicity therefore avoid folly, in wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, malice. Prudence without
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169921:6"/> ſimplicity is the mother of evill doing; ſimplicity without pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is the mother of evill ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering; but prudence &amp; ſimplicity joyned together, are like the two fires <hi>Caſtor</hi> &amp; <hi>Pollux,</hi> whereof if one appear alone unto the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, it threatneth ſhipwrack, but both together promiſe a ſafe harbour: So prudence and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity joyned together, doe cauſe all the actions for which we embarque our ſelves, to arrive at the port of proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſucceſſe; but parted aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſhipwrack our ſouls on the rocks of malice, or the flats of folly. Therefore, as the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubims</hi> over the Ark had their faces towards each other, and both toward the mercy ſeat; ſo muſt prudence and ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city be joyned together, and both will tend unto bleſſedneſs.</p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:169921:7"/>
                  <p>Prudence is practicall wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and is (in the generall) of verie large extent, conſiſting in the knowledge of what is beſt and fitteſt to be done in all emergent occaſions, and in working accordingly. It hath alſo divers parts, and divers kinds, which I intend not to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue; my purpoſe only being to ſpeak of it ſo farr forth and no further, than it may be attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſome particular actions of the Serpent, wherein there is (though not a realitie, which is properly the habit of a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſoul) yet a reſemblance of ſpirituall wiſdome, by our Saviour thought worthie our imitation. Which exhortation, though directed immediatly to the Apoſtles only, yet is applya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to every Chriſtian. And as our Sauiour ſaid to his auditors
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169921:7"/> concerning watching; <hi>What I ſay unto you, I ſay unto all, watch:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke. 13.37.</note> So what he ſaith in this caſe to his Apoſtles, he ſaith unto all Chriſtians, <hi>Bee prudent as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, and ſimple as doves.</hi> What therefore the cabinet of truth, grave hiſtorie, hath preſerved for us, concerning the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome-preſenting qualities of the Serpent, I will unlock, and proportionate our imitating actions unto their juſt meaſure. Now the Prudence of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent whereon our imitation muſt attend, doth emblazon it ſelf in divers particulars, which are theſe that follow.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                  <p>THE firſt is the renewing of his youth, with the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169921:8"/> handmaids thereof, the vigor of his ſenſes and their opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; which he effecteth on this manner. When he feeleth the heavie plummets of age ſwiftly moving toward their end, the wheeles of the clock of life he thus winds up again, He faſteth certain dayes (ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>) whereby his body is dryed, and his skin looſened, then by the eating of a certain bitter herb, he doth vomit up a virulent poyſonous humour, which was the cauſe of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity: at length, that he may temper the roughneſſe of his skin, he bathes himſelf in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and ſeeking a narrow chink or hole in ſome rock or other place, he wriggles him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in, and forceably drawing himſelf through ſlips off his skin; and laſtly, reſting in ſome ſuch
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169921:8"/> place, where the ſun doth moſt favourably diſplay his beams, he recovers a new skin, and hardens it fit for his uſe; and with it, inveſteth himſelf with new vigor, adding thereby cleeneſſe to his eyeſight, ſtrength to his bodyes motion, increaſe to his ſtomacks appetite and digeſtion: and by this meanes doth he renew the almoſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired league between his bodie and his ſoul. This alſo affirmeth both <hi>Avicen</hi> and <hi>Pliny.</hi> To this line of the Serpents example, muſt we apply our imitation; renewing our lives by the works of Penance. Firſt by Faſting, whereby wee ſhall dry up the flux of Intemperance; then by taking down into our hearts a doſe of the bitter herb of of Contrition, whereby wee muſt vomit up of the poyſon of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169921:9"/> ſin, at our mouths by Confeſſion; and waſhing our ſelves in our tears, and in the river of the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary the word of God, paſſing through the ſtraits of a firm re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to ſerve God and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake ſin, we muſt put off the old man with the luſts therof; and by the heat of the ſun, the love of Chriſt, drying up our facilitie and proneſs unto ſin, we muſt <hi>put on the new man,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ephes. 4.24.</note> 
                     <hi>which is created according unto God in juſtice and holineſs of truth:</hi> and ſo recovering new ſtrength unto well-doeing, wee ſhall more cleerly underſtand ſpirituall things, more ardently affect God and our neighbour, and more earneſtly hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſſe: and thus ſhall wee renew again the life of grace in our decayed ſouls.</p>
                  <p>As abſtemious <hi>John Baptiſt</hi>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:169921:9"/> was the fore-runner of the birth of Chriſt, ſo muſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence uſher the new birth of a Chriſtian; but the devill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters into the voluptuous, as he did into the herd of ſwin; or as into <hi>Judas,</hi> when he had eaten the ſop. Prayer, the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon by which wee overcome even God himſelf, is by no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo much ſharpened, as by Faſting. And therefore, in the whole current of Scripture, ſhall wee find theſe two in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of holy men linked together, like the bells and pomegranates on the veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Aaron;</hi> Prayer rendring a ſweet ſound, Faſting a ſweet ſmel; which is therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to cinamon and balſum, which drying up the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of dead bodies, keep them ſweet. <hi>Cúm,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">S. Aug.</note> 
                     <hi>caro areſcit per
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169921:10"/> abſtinentiam ab humore luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae, tunc reddit deo odorem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinentiae: when the humor of luxurie is dryed up in our fleſh by abſtinence, then doe wee ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der unto God the ſweet odor of continence.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Neh. 1.4.</note> The Prophet <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia</hi> ſaith, <hi>When I heard theſe words, I ſate down, and wept, and mourned many dayes; I faſted and prayed before the face of the God of heaven.</hi> Alſo the Prophet Daniel,<note place="margin">Dan. 9.3.</note> 
                     <hi>I turned my face unto my Lord God, to ask and beſeech in faſting, ſackcloth, and aſhes.</hi> And then did he receive an eſpeciall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation concerning the birth and death of Chriſt. <hi>St. Peter,</hi> when he was faſting ſaw the viſion in the houſe of <hi>Simon</hi> the tanner, <hi>Acts</hi> 10. Alſo <hi>Acts</hi> 13.2. <hi>As they miniſtred unto our Lord and faſted, the Holy
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169921:10"/> Ghoſt ſaid unto them, ſeparate</hi> Barnabas <hi>and</hi> Saul <hi>for the work whereunto I have taken them.</hi> Here wee ſee that faſting-pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is moſt pleaſing unto God, even as emptie-bellied inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, are ſweeteſt to the eares of men. <hi>Facilius per jejunium oratio penetrat coelum,</hi> ſaith S. Jſodore; <hi>The darts of our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers being headed with faſting, doe more eaſily pierce the heavens.</hi> And as faſting-ſpittle, as <hi>Pliny</hi> ſaith, kills a ſerpent; ſo doth faſting-prayer put the devill to flight; and with him, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny troups of his temptations, wherewith he aſſults our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed ſenſes. And therefore our Saviour buckling himſelf to grapple with the devill, made this one peece of his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, as the Scripture ſaith, <hi>He faſted forty dayes and forty
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169921:11"/> nights.</hi> S. Auguſt, ſaith, <hi>Faſting doth purge the mind, it engligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens the ſoul, it ſubdues the fleſsh unto the ſpirit, and moulds in a man an humble and contrite heart.</hi> It purgeth the mind, by conſuming and drying up the humour of luxury: even as the fire which came down from heaven, licked up the water about the ſacrifice of <hi>Elias.</hi> It enlightens the ſoul, by light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the bodie, and freeing it from thoſe clogs of fleſh, to which in not a few it is a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner: for the bellies fullneſſe, is mother of the minds dull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and repletions of meat in the body, breed obſtructions of vice in the ſoul: whence ſaith the Prophet <hi>David,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 34.13.</note> 
                     <hi>Their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie hath proceeded as it were out of fatneſſe;</hi> then immediatly followes, <hi>They have thought
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169921:11"/> and ſpoken wickedneſſe.</hi> It ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dues the fleſh unto the Spirit, by ſtriking the ſwelling ſayls of pride and incontinence, ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling us to ſay with S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.27.</note> 
                     <hi>I chaſtiſe my body, and bring it into ſervitude:</hi> and like <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> it caſts out the bondwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and her children, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill with his ſpawn of ſin, not ſuffering the handmaids of our affections, to advance them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt their miſtreſſe reaſon. And laſtly, it makes our ſouls humble and contrite, as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 72.7.</note> 
                     <hi>I did humble my ſoul with faſting.</hi> And this is the ſecond condition required in the renewing of our leaſe of life.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Paſſeover</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be eaten with bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter herbs;<note place="margin">Exod. 12.8.</note> and they that will feed profitably upon <hi>Chriſt</hi>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:169921:12"/> our <hi>Paſſeover,</hi> muſt have their hearts embittered with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction and ſorrow for their ſins. Surgeons when a bone that hath been broken is ſet awry, are forced that they may ſet it right, to break it again; ſo the rectitude of our ſouls being broken by our fall in <hi>Adam,</hi> whereby we goe halting all our lives after, that we may ſet our hearts aright, which are thus wryed and crookeded by ſin, we muſt break them again, by an humble ſorrow for all our ſins. Which muſt not continue for one aſſault alone, but wee muſt multiply our ſtroaks and breakings of our hard hearts, untill our ſorrow ſwim in our eys, and furrow our faces with our tears: even as <hi>Moſes</hi> by ſtriking the rock twice, made a river of water to guſh forth.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169921:12"/> And we muſt be ſorry, that we can be no more ſorry, and with the men of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Kings, 30.</note> 
                     <hi>weep till we can weep no more.</hi> It is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to afflict our ſouls and bow down our heads for a day; or to be like the marble, which is moyſt only againſt wet wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to weep only when the threatning ſtorms of puniſhment hang over our heads, remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſtill inwardly as hard as the marble: For as S. <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> ſaith, <hi>Hee that bewayleth his ſins, yet doth not forſake them, makes himſelf lyable to ſo much the greater puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by how much he contemns that pardon which hee might have attained by weeping.</hi> But if like the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> wee paſs through the red Sea of our tears of true Contrition, we ſhall leave all the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> our
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169921:13"/> ſins, overwhelmed therein S. <hi>Aug.</hi> ſaith, <hi>as Grief is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of repentance, ſo Tears are the witneſſes of grief;</hi> into which, if wee can melt our ſelves, like <hi>Niobe,</hi> through thoſe dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full images, which ſorrow im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prints in our over-tender hearts, for our outward loſſes of goods, or friends, or the like; and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſchannell one rivolet from the fountains of our eys, as a tribute due for the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean of ſorrow, which we owe unto the cauſe of thoſe loſſes, our ſins; ſurely, we have either no ſenſe of our ſins, which is bad; or no fear of Gods judgements, which is worſe; or no love unto his goodneſs, which is worſt of all. For if we had, the heat of that love would reflect ſo ſtrongly on our hearts clouded with ſin, that it
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169921:13"/> would wholly diſſolve them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to tearfull ſorrow; even as the Sun printing hard his hot beams upon a groſs thick cloud, powrs it down into rain.</p>
                  <p>The Prophet <hi>David</hi> was of a far other temper, and yet had an excuſe as colourable as any one; being a man, and amongſt men a ſouldier, and amongſt ſouldiers one of the hardieſt, whom no danger could reach to fear, no temporall domage to grieve; and yet ſuch impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion did ſorrow make in his heart for ſin, that he ſaith, <hi>I will waſh my bed every night, and water my Couch with my tears.</hi> O faelices lachrymae quas beata manus conditoris abſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get; ſaith S. <hi>Bernard; O thoſe happy tears which the favourable hand of God ſhall wipe away;</hi> And O thoſe happy eys which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169921:14"/> have choſen rather to melt themſelves into ſuch tears, than to lift themſelves up with pride, to look aſide with diſdain, or aſquint with envy. Theſe tears of Compunction and ſorrow for our ſins, doe afford us the ſame refreſhing, that taking of ſoyl doth unto the hunted deer; who being hotly purſued by hellhounds, the Devill and his temptations, and our hearts emboſt and panting under their purſute, are wonderfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh'd and reſtor'd to our loſt ſtrength, by waſhing our ſelves in the bath of our relenting tears: into which who ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as into the troubled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Betheſda</hi>'s pool, is aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly healed of his ſins. If then the bitter ſorrow for ſin, be the mother of ſuch ſweet and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for effects, let us ſeal up
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169921:14"/> our deſires with the words of S. <hi>Aug. Let repentance, bitter repentance, be the continuall companion of my days; grief, continuall grief, the inſatiate terror of my life; and if I be not worthy to lift up my eys to heaven in prayer, yet at leaſt I am worthy to put them out with weeping.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. III.</head>
                  <p>THe third thing required to the renewing of our lives, is Confeſſion. The Dog, when his ſtomack is ſurcharged with any hurtfull meat, by eating graſs vomits it up again: ſo when we have burthened our conſciences with ever-hurtfull ſin, wee muſt by eating the bitter herb of Contrition, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorge
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169921:15"/> our ſins at our mouths by Confeſſion. For as in a wound, ſo long as the iron, or ſteel, or any part of that which gave the wound, remains, it obſtructs the healing; ſo doe the remains of ſin in the Conſcience through non confeſſion control the influence of any remedy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed thereunto; as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Prov. 28.13.</note> 
                     <hi>He that hideth his ſins ſhall not be directed, but he that ſhall confeſs and forſake them, ſhall obtain mercy.</hi> An impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtume breaking inwardly, threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens death unto the party; but outwardly it is a means to purge and cleanſe the body: So ſin ſuppreſſed and ſmothered within our hearts, doth empoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and choak our ſouls; but breaking out at our mouths by Confeſſion, it doth purge and clear the conſcience, and like
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169921:15"/> the breaking out of the lips in an ague, is a ſign of our amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: So as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.10.</note> 
                     <hi>With the mouth confeſſion is made unto ſalvation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which Confeſſion that it may be thus profitable, muſt be alſo generall. When a mans body ſweats all over (ſay the Phyſicians) it is a ſign of ſtrength of nature; but if it ſweat in ſome parts and not in others, it is a ſymptom of debility and weakneſs: and no leſs teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is it of the weakneſs and wickedneſs of the ſoul, if wee doe not purge our ſouls uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally of all our ſins. Theſe parcell Confeſſors, are like the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who caſt out moſt of the heathen out of the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> yet ſuffered the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> to remain, and made a league with them; who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169921:16"/> became <hi>as nails in their eys,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Num. 33.55.</note> 
                     <hi>and ſpears in their ſides:</hi> ſo the leaſt ſin that remains with us uncaſt out by Confeſſion, will be a prick unto our conſciences, and an inſtrument of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Now Confeſſion as it muſt be accompanied by u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſality, ſo it muſt be uſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by examination; whereby looking back into the book of our conſciences, wherein the names of all our ſins are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, we muſt awaken the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of all our thoughts, words, and deeds, and muſter them up together, that ſo by Conſeſſion they may be caſt forth: as a ſick man, who being about to take a Purge firſt takes a Preparative to open the paſſages, that ſo by the purge they may be the more eaſily ejected.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:169921:16"/>
                  <p>And that we may amongſt the millions of our actions, know which of them are to be ſuperſcribed with the title of ſin, we muſt have recourſe unto the word of God, as it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded unto us by the Church, and the Paſtors thereof; which like the Mariners card and compaſs, will demonſtrate unto us, how neer or far off our actions are, from the immove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able North Pole of Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandemants. And as when the Sun ſhineth not into a houſe, the ayr ſeemeth clear; but if it once enter in at the window, it then appears full of motes and duſt: ſo the light of Gods word ſhining in our underſtandings, will diſcover an infinite number of ſins, which before its acceſs, wee could neither perceive, nor
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169921:17"/> would we believe. And as the word of God doth ſhew us our faults, ſo alſo doth it cleanſe them, like unto a baſon of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, wherein a man may both ſee the ſpots in his face, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he may waſh them away: as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſ. 118 9.</note> 
                     <hi>How ſhall a young man amend his way? by keeping of thy words.</hi> In this word of God therefore, this river of the Sanctuary, in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Serpent, muſt we waſh our ſelves; which not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like a certain water in <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia,</hi> which being drank by the Sheep, maketh them white; ſo this received into our hearts, doth blanch our ſouls with the whiteneſs of innocence. Now where the Well of Gods word is deep, and a ſtone rowled on the mouth thereof, that is, is hard to be underſtood, with
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169921:17"/> 
                     <hi>Rachel,</hi> mentioned in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.9.</note> we muſt get ſome <hi>Jaacob</hi> to remove it; that is, ſome one that hath wreſtled with God, as the name of <hi>Jaacob</hi> ſignifies, and that hath thereby obtained his aſſiſtance unto his ſtudies and endeavours, that ſo he may adminiſter unto us. But let us beware, above all things, that wee doe not drink down the water of Gods word, with the abuſive interpretation of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques; for then contrary to the former effect of the Macedoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an water, it will be like that water in the troughes, for the ſheep, wherein <hi>Jaacob</hi> laid his pilled rods, which made them bring forth ſpotted lambs; ſo will this make us bring forth opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons erroneous, black and foul.</p>
                  <p>The ſerpent, as I ſaid in the beginning, after his faſting, his eating a bitter herb, his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169921:18"/> caſting up a poyſonous humour, and his bathing himfelf in water, ſeekes ſome narrow hole, through which drawing himſelf, he ſlips off his old skin; and drying his ſlipperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the ſun, recovers a new one: ſo wee, after our faſting our eating of the bitter herb of contrition, and vomiting our poyſonous ſins at our mouths by Confeſſion, and having waſhed our ſelves in the water of Gods word, muſt (paſſing through the ſtreights of a firm reſolution to forſake our ſins, and to ſerve God,) put off the old man with the luſts thereof; and by the heat of the love of Chriſt, drying up our proneneſſe unto ſin, <hi>put on the new man,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ephes. 4.24.</note> 
                     <hi>which is created ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording unto God in juſtice, and holyneſſe of truth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:169921:18"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Streight is the gate,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 7.14.</note> 
                     <hi>and narrow is the way</hi> (Saith our Saviour) <hi>which leadeth unto life;</hi> through this ſtreight way muſt wee reſolve to paſſe, that ſo wee may deveſt our ſelves of the old-man, and inveſt our ſelves with the new; by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting from evill, and turning unto good. <hi>Ceaſe to doe evill,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eſay. 1.16.17.</note> 
                     <hi>learn to doe well;</hi> ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Eſayas. <hi>Eſchew evill and doe good,</hi> ſaith the prophet <hi>David.</hi> 'Tis ſaid,<note place="margin">Pſal. 36.27.</note> that when the Eagle groweth old, his beak is ſo crooked that he cannot eat his meat; he therefore goes to a rock, beates his beak againſt it, untill he have broken it off, and then falls to his meat, and growes young again. So our hearts growing crooked toward the earth and earthy things, whereby wee cannot
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169921:19"/> receive the ſpirituall food of Gods word, and Sacraments, wee muſt ſtrike them againſt the rock <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> by conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both his precepts and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; whereby the crooked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our beaks ſhall be broken; that is, our earthly affections rectified, and our ſouls directed unto God; whereby wee ſhalbe enabled to feed upon Chriſt in his Word and Sacraments, and ſo renew again our youth. As it is Pſal. 102.5. <hi>Who fileth thy deſire with good things, and thy youth ſhall be renewed as the eagles.</hi> And as <hi>Samuels</hi> mother,<note place="margin">1. Kings, 2.19.</note> (as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith) brought him a new coat at ſet times, when ſhe went up to offer the yearly ſacrifice; ſo as often as wee offer the ſin-offering of a contrite heart unto God, wee muſt, caſting off the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169921:19"/> old rags of ſin, cloth our-ſelves with the new robes of juſtice. For wee muſt not think to wear this new coat with our old; to wear the linſy-wolſy garments of religion and word<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſſe together; a thing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden in the old law; nor yet with the Jewes, to cry hayl unto Chriſt, and yet crucify him; to make a profeſſion of him in words, and contradict it in deeds, This is to ſerve <hi>God and mammon;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 9.16.17.</note> to put <hi>new wine</hi> into <hi>old veſſells,</hi> to patch <hi>old garments</hi> with <hi>new cloth,</hi> which as our Saviour ſaith, is either impoſſible, or dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous: therefore, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.19.</note> 
                     <hi>Whoſoever nameth the name of our Lord, let him depart from iniquitie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Moyſes</hi> when he went into the holy mount, put off his
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169921:20"/> ſhooes; <hi>Elias</hi> when he aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into heaven, caſt off his mantle; and <hi>Eliſha</hi> when he went to ſerve the Prophet, bad adieu to his father and mother: ſo when wee enliſt our ſelves in the catalogue of Gods ſervants, wee muſt put off the ſhooes of our evill affections; we muſt caſt off the cloak of our unrighteouſneſſe; and take our leaves of all thoſe ſins, which either through our proneneſſe unto them, or their long familiarity and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with us, have ſo endeared themſelves unto us, that wee are forced to reproach our ſelves with the title of their acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. <hi>Moyſes</hi> commanded that they that went unto the tabernacle, ſhould goe out of the Camp; and we out of our ſins, if we will goe unto Chriſt.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169921:20"/> 
                     <hi>Wherefore,</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.13.</note> 
                     <hi>let us goe out unto him without the Camp.</hi> And being once out, let us not prove retrograde in the ſphear of goodneſſe; nor with <hi>Lots</hi> wife look back unto <hi>Sodom;</hi> nor ſay of any ſin, as <hi>Lot</hi> did of <hi>Zoar,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 19.20.</note> 
                     <hi>Is it not a little one?</hi> It is certain, the devill will be tempting of us to turn back, and ſay unto us, as <hi>Solomons</hi> mother did to him; <hi>I have a ſmall ſute unto thee,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">3. Kings. 2.22.</note> 
                     <hi>I pray deny mee not;</hi> to which if wee yeeld, as he foreſaw, ſo wee ſhall find, that it will coſt us no leſſe than the loſſe of the kingdome, even the kingdome of heaven. Therefore, having once caſt out the old <hi>Adam</hi> out of the Paradiſe of our ſouls, let us place there the Cherubin of grace with the flaming ſword of the Spirit, to reſiſt the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169921:21"/> entrance of ſin: and in all the temptations of the world, the fleſh, and the devill unto ſin, let us anſwer in the words of the ſpouſe in the Canticles, <hi>I have put off my coat,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cant. 5.3.</note> 
                     <hi>how ſhall I put it on? I have waſhed my feet, how ſhall I defile them?</hi> And thus if we be renewed; as the ſerpent, by recovering a new skin, doth with it reſume new ſtrength, ſees more cleerely, moves more lively, feeds more hartily; ſo ſhall wee, by this means, enrich our ſelves with the ſtrength of well doing; wee ſhall more cleerely under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ſpirituall myſteries; wee ſhall walk more uprightly in the love of God and of our neighbour; wee ſhall more eagerly feed on and more ſtrongly digeſt the ſpirituall food of Gods word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169921:21"/> by the nouriſhment whereof, we ſhall walk from grace to grace, untill wee come to be perfect men in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> from grace unto glory, untill wee be perfect Saints in the kingdome of heaven.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
                  <p>A Second property of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the ſerpent, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy our imitation, is this; The ſerpent by reaſon of that enmity which it hath with mankind, to ſecure it ſelf from the danger of mens invaſions, creepeth away and hideth it ſelf under buſhes, and delighteth to dwell in deſarts, and unfrequented places: ſo the children of God, mindfull of that irreconcilable
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169921:22"/> enmity which God hath put betwixt that old myſticall ſerpent the devill, with his viperous brood, wicked men, and the ſeed of the woman, the Children of the holy Church, ſhould ſhroud them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under Gods protection, who appeared unto <hi>Mayſes</hi> in a buſh; and with <hi>Enoch,</hi> walk with God in the deſart of divine contemplation; that ſo they may baulk the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, and the conſequents thereof, the miſchiefs of the wicked.</p>
                  <p>The Poets feign of <hi>Arachne,</hi> that contending with <hi>Pallas,</hi> for the prize in workmanſhip, and being conquered by her, disdaining at the ill ſucceſſe of her enterprize, ſhe did ſo ſwell with the poyſon of envy and hatred, that ſhe turn'd into a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169921:22"/> Spider: ſo the devill in the pride of his thoughts, contending with his Maker, and by him, like lightning, being caſt down from heaven, hath had his nature ever ſince transformed into a ſerpent, full of the deadly poyſon of envy and hatred againſt God, and all good men: continually aſſaulting them, either by battery, or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myning; by open force, or ſecret fraud; by the feirceneſſe of the lion, or ſubtilty of the ſerpent. Which enmity of the devill againſt God, like that which often happens betwixt the fathers of two potent fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies here on earth, hath devolved it ſelf unto each others poſterity; who like <hi>Jaacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> ſtruggle in the worlds womb, the earth, as if ſo little a room were too ſtreight
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169921:23"/> a dwelling for ſo great enemies. Which enmity unveiled it ſelf in the worlds infancy betwixt <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abell;</hi> who (as the Poets feign) like the ſerpents teeth ſown by <hi>Cadmus,</hi> were no ſooner grown up, but the one deſtroyed the other: <hi>Iſmael</hi> ſcoffed at his brother <hi>Jſaac; Micol</hi> laughed at her husband <hi>David,</hi> and king <hi>Ahab</hi> hated the Prophet <hi>Micaiah;</hi> and the reaſon was, becauſe he told the truth. It is the godlies good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that purchaſeth them hatred for as likeneſſe is the cauſe of liking ſo the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of manners produceth contrary affections. God is light, the godly are enlightned; God is truth, the godly are true: the devill is the Prince of darkneſs, the wicked are darkned; the devill is the Father of lyes, the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169921:23"/> wicked are lyars; what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion then betwixt light and darkneſſe, truth and falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Belial,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">John. 15.19.</note> God and the devill? <hi>Becauſe yee are not of the world,</hi> ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>therefore the world hateth you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now this hatred diſcovers it ſelf, either againſt our bodies, or our ſouls; either (as the Scripture ſpeaketh) like the great Bulls of <hi>Baſon</hi> they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſe us on every ſide; or like the little foxes, they deſtroy Gods vineyard. Thus in the dawning of the Churches day, by the tyranny of the wicked, did the Prophets and holy men of God fall like the morning dew and the ſeeds of grace which themſelves had ſown, they watred with their own blood. Thus the holy Chriſtian
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169921:24"/> Martyrs in the noontide of the Churches day, when the ſun of perſecution reflected on them as hotly as the noon-ſun on <hi>Jonas</hi> head, did calmly bleed oyl to the Apoſtles lamps, whoſe bright flames yet ſerve to light Poſterity to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Thus alſo theſe latter ages in ſome places, and at ſome times, have paid as large a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute of patience to heaven, and ſufferance in the world; as any that went before them; and have conſtantly kept the faith, untill they loſt themſelves in keeping it; like <hi>Naboth,</hi> who kept his poſſeſſion, with the loſſe of his blood. And thus in all ages have the diamonds of the world, the godly, who were made to be pretiouſly ſet in the eſteem of men, been brought to the extremeſt degree
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169921:24"/> of calamity, that witty cruelty could invent, or unrelenting malice execute. And thus alſo did the non-ſuch of well-doing and evill ſuffering, our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, by the malice and cruelty of the Jews, ſurrender up a life more ſpotleſs than in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, unto a death moſt ſhamefull and ignominious, even to the death of the Croſs; the horror of whoſe torments, left not where to adde unto it, by the wiſhes of his enemies. <hi>And if they doe theſe things in the green wood,</hi> ſaith he himſelf,<note place="margin">Luke 23.31.</note> 
                     <hi>what ſhall be done in the dry?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nor doth the malice of the devill and wicked men ſtint it ſelf here, or ſatisfie it ſelf with the ſuffering of our bodies; then were their aſſaults little, their victories leſs; ſeeing that the vertuous, like the palm tree,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:169921:25"/> ſpring up by preſſing; and like the Vine, ſpread further by pruning. The rod of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, like <hi>Aarons</hi> rod that budded, doth encreaſe the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, both for number and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, making them both more and better. Therefore doth the devill lay ſiege unto our ſouls by the temptations of proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and pleaſure alſo, hoping that (as it is in the fable of the Wind and Sun, ſtriving who ſhould make the wayfaring man put off his cloke) what foul means cannot, fair means may effect. In which his two main engines are the fleſh, and the world; the fleſh within us, the world without us. The fleſh, he corrupteth with bliſs-promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſuggeſtions; which like a treacherous Citizen, betrayeth the fort of our will, into the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169921:25"/> hand of him our enemy; and thus <hi>a mans enemies are</hi> (as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſaid they ſhould be,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.36.</note>) <hi>thoſe of a mans own houſe.</hi> But with no better ſucceſs then <hi>Tarpeia</hi> the Veſtall Nun betrayed the Capitoll, bargaining for the bracelets on the enemies hands; who when they were entred, did not caſt their bracelets on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but their bucklers alſo into her lap, which with their weight preſt her to death. Even ſo the devill many times over-ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying mens unlawfull fleſhly deſires, with their ſinfull weight, preſſeth their ſouls into the pit of deſtruction.</p>
                  <p>The world alſo, I mean the wicked men thereof, he ſets like ſo many lime-twigs and ſnares to entrap our ſouls: and as fiſher-men doe make one fiſh a bait to catch another, ſo the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:169921:26"/> devill doth make a bad man, a bait to catch a good. Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men are moſt pernicious creatures, and eaſily pull down vengeance upon others, either by the deſert of their ſin, or by the infection: who, like men that have the plague, out of a malignity of diſpoſition which attends upon their diſeaſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to infect others, and to draw them, as the ſcripture ſaith, <hi>to the ſame confuſion of luxury,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.4.</note> 
                     <hi>with themſelves. Vicia ad vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinos ſerpunt &amp; contactu nocent,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca:</hi> Sin amongſt men is like the rot amongſt Sheep, of a catching and infectious quality: and he that thinks to partake the company of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, and not participate of their vices, multiplies the miracles, where walkers on the water, with <hi>Peter,</hi> are not
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169921:26"/> drowned; and in the fire, with the three children, are not burnt. <hi>The nature of things is ſuch,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Chriſoſtome, that where a good man is joyned with a bad, the bad is not bettered by the good, but the good corrupted by the bad.</hi> As ſickneſs, by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying the ſick, is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to the healthy, but not ſo health unto the ſick. And as the <hi>Salamander</hi> extinguiſheth the fire, and is not burnt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; ſo the wicked amongſt the godly, are ready to quench the heat of their vertue, and not to be enflamed thereby. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul Be not companions with them: Joſeph</hi> by living in the Court, learned to ſwear by the life of <hi>Pharoah;</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> when he was amongſt the high Prieſts ſervants denyed his maſter. The
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169921:27"/> warmer hee was by the high Prieſts fire, the colder he grew in love towards God.<note place="margin">Pſal. 105.35.</note> 
                     <hi>They were mingled among the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> of the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and what was the iſſue? <hi>They learned their works.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore, as our Saviour adviſeth us, <hi>Beware of men.</hi> Firſt of men whoſe cruelty no meekneſs can aſſwage; of men, whoſe blood-thirſtineſs no lives can quench; of men, from whoſe perſecutions no place is ſecure; and if they perſecute you in one City, fly into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; let a diſcreet fear give wings unto your feet, and a godly confidence ſteel unto your hearts. If opportunity open a way unto your flight, refuſe it not; if not, let an unrebated reſolution arm you for ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:169921:27"/> Beware alſo of the company of wicked men, who like bemyred dogs defile with fawning: For howſoever fiſhes living in the ſalt water retain a freſh taſt, and ſavour not of the briniſh quality of the Sea wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they live; and it may bee true, which <hi>Solinus</hi> reports of the river <hi>Tigris</hi> in <hi>Armenia,</hi> that it paſſeth many miles through the lake of <hi>Arethuſa,</hi> and yet mingles neither fiſhes nor waters with the lake, but is quite of an other colour from the ſame; yet, <q>Inficitur terrae ſordibus unda fluens:</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>Clear running ſtreams are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the neighbourhood of filthy ſoyls;</q> and pure men with the ſoul converſation of the wicked. Swallows (they ſay) would not build in <hi>Thebes,</hi>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:169921:28"/> becauſe the wals thereof were ſo often beſieged; nor let good men, or thoſe that deſire to be ſuch, haſten to the company of thoſe, whoſe mind-infecting manners, doe threaten their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.<note place="margin">Apoc. 18.4.</note> 
                     <hi>Be not partakers of her ſins, that ye receive not of her plagues,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>John.</hi> The reaſon why our Saviour would not give the Diſciple, mentioned in the Goſpell, leave to goe back to bury his dead Father, was (ſay ſome Divines) leſt his unbelieving kinred ſhould cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt him again; for bad men keep others from goodneſs, as the dead carcaſſes did the raven from <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark. It was part of the vow of the <hi>Nazarites,</hi> not to defile themſelves with dead bodies; no more ſhould good men ſtain themſelves with the dead converſation of the wicked.</p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:169921:28"/>
                  <p>Run we then from theſe, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did from his rod turned to a Serpent; for if we joyn our ſelves to <hi>Beelphegor,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 105.27.</note> we will, like the children of <hi>Iſrael, eat the offerings of the dead.</hi> And to decline the cruelty of ſome, in the deſtruction of our bodies, whoſe rage knoweth no mean; let us wiſely (with the Serpent) fly into the wilderneſs, where we ſhall find <hi>Jeſus</hi> the Lion of the tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> and the braſen Serpent, which was there lifted up, who will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter for us with that roring Lion and ſubtil Serpent the devill, with his viperous gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and either reſcue us, or revenge our evils. And to avoid the contagious company of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whoſe motions, although more ſilent, yet not leſs deep or dangerous than the other;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:169921:29"/> yea much more, for this like lightning which melts the ſword, but hurts not the ſcab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard, paſſeth through our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and empoyſons our Souls with the inſinuating venome of ſin: let us (with the Serpent) hide our ſelves in the holes of the rock, in the wounds of the rock <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> whoſe blood is more Antidote, than all the ſins of the Univerſe can be Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: ſo ſhall we avoid both the bodily and ſpirituall dangers whereunto the cruelty of ſome and the contagion of other wicked men would expoſe us.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:169921:29"/>
                  <head>CHAP. V.</head>
                  <p>ANother work of prudence in the actions of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, by juſt title claming our imitation, is this: The Serpent if he be aſſaulted, his chiefeſt care is directed to the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his Head, for which he expoſeth his whole body to the danger; knowing that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is the caſtle of his life; in ſo much that when he is in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, he winds himſelf round into many rings, placing his head in the center; and (as <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> ſaith) if he have but two fingers length of his body left with his head, his life will ſtill remain in him: in like manner ſhould our endeavours bend themſelves to hold our head <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and that which doth knit and cyment us to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:169921:30"/> 
                     <hi>Chriſt,</hi> true faith and charity: for the ſafeguard whereof, we ſhould expoſe all elſe to hazard, and in compriſon whereof, we ſhould neglect whatſoever of profit or delight the world can adde unto us; and ſay with S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Phil 3.8.</note> 
                     <hi>I account all things as dung, that I may gain Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Natura eſt ſui conſervativa,</hi> ſaith Philoſophy, <hi>it is inbred in the nature of each thing, to endeavour its own preſervation;</hi> ſo is it in the nature of grace: now when wee cannot keep our ſelves from the endomage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all parts, wee muſt learn from the wiſe Serpent, that our care of preſervation muſt chiefly be directed unto that, whoſe well-being doth chiefly concern us. The foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of life in a Serpent, is in the head; and the life of a Chriſtian is in Chriſt, who is
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:169921:30"/> the head of his Church; as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.3.</note> 
                     <hi>your life is hid with Chriſt in God.</hi> If then our proſperity, wealth, honour, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, or ought elſe that wee enjoy, cannot bee compatible with the preſervation of our head <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> more than the ark of God in the temple of <hi>Dagon;</hi> and that a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſuffering of evill, muſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly free us from the danger of doing evill; of evils the leaſt muſt fall under our election, and wee muſt chooſe rather (with S. <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles) to leave all and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt, than with <hi>Demas,</hi> to forſake Chriſt and follow the world. <hi>Skin for skin,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Job 2.4.</note> 
                     <hi>and all that a man hath will he give for his life,</hi> ſaid the devill, and truly, of <hi>Job<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> wealth, honour, liberty, worldly peace, wife,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:169921:31"/> children, and friends, which are but skins, things ſlight, triviall, and ſuperficiall in compariſon, muſt we part with, to preſerve the life of our ſouls, by the true faith, and love of Chriſt; for he that doth not forſake all, if need be, for him, is not worthy of him; as he himſelf teſtifieth. And what <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaid of his Country, which he held ſecond to nothing in the merit of his reſpect, we may more truly ſay of Chriſt, and true religion; <hi>Cari ſunt parentes, liberi, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinqui, amici, at omnes omnium charitates patria una complexa eſt;</hi> Our Parents are dear unto us, ſo are our children, our kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and acquaintance, but all the love of thoſe, doth Religion alone comprize. If we did but juſtly poyſe the poverty of the worlds great riches, and the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:169921:31"/> riches of a good Chriſtian in his greateſt poverty; who hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Chriſt, hath with him, the treaſures of wiſdom, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, who is the Magazine and Storehouſe of them all; wee would count it a piece of folly in that man, who ſhould aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the one, to abound in the other, below the degree of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau's,</hi> who ſold his birrh right for a meſs of pottage, or of <hi>Eſop's dog,</hi> who ſnapping at the ſhadow, let goe the ſubſtance. O how much better is it to ſit on <hi>Iobs</hi> dunghill, and with him <hi>to know that our Redeemer li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth;</hi> than in <hi>Solomons</hi> throne with the Kings of the earth, or in <hi>Moyſes</hi> chair with the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees, and to bandy our ſelves againſt Gods annointed</hi> with the one; and <hi>to ſay well, and not doe it,</hi> with the other.</p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:169921:32"/>
                  <p>Moſt true it is, that very many of the Children of God, like the ark of the teſtament, which was continually hurried from place to place, untill it was ſetled in the glorious temple of <hi>Solomon;</hi> ſo are they, untill they be ſetled in the more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious kingdome of heaven. And like <hi>Noahs</hi> Dove, which found no reſt untill it returned to the ark; ſo they have their bodyes worn with continuall afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; untill they be layed up in the common wardrob of the grave. They are expoſed to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as many miſeries, as they live minutes; no place being ſo barren of trouble, but can afford them a full-handed harveſt thereof. <hi>They wander,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.27.</note> 
                     <hi>in ſheepskins and goatskins, being in want, ſtraitned, and afflicted:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:169921:32"/> though the floods of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on lift up their waves, and are ready to overwhelm their ſouls; and the windes of temptation as ready to overturn them; yet if with St. <hi>Peter</hi> they can ſtretch forth the hands of their faith unto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he will pluck their feet out of the danger that gapeth for them, and cover them with the wings of his protection, as the Mercy-Seat covered the ark. And as the Serpent, if he have but a ſmall part of his body joyned to his head, he ſtill lives: So the afflictions of the children of God, though they take from them all that this world hath added to them, yea their bodyes from their ſouls, if yet they keep their ſouls united unto Chriſt their head, they ſtill preſerve their lives uncouquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:169921:33"/> when as the wicked, whom every breath of diſaſter driveth away, whom the ſatisfying of every ſinfull deſire ſhall force from that power of godlyneſſe which they ought in each action to expreſſe, are dead while they live: as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle S. <hi>Jude</hi> ſaith;<note place="margin">Jude. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>twice dead, and plucked up by the rootes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If therefore the unſtinted malice of the devill, ſhould leave us with <hi>Iob,</hi> as naked as when wee came out of our mothers womb; rob us of the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our earthly eternity, and our loves greateſt inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, our children; deprive us of our lives ſweeteſt compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, our health; and print our bodyes more full of boyles and ſores than <hi>Dive's</hi> dogs could have licked; and which
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:169921:33"/> doubles all theſe, leave us no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a Wife, whoſe weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe he corrupteth, as he did in Paradiſe, to become a fellow-tempter with himſelf; and friends, who in the depth of of this Miſery ſhall rather make our griefs ſmart more with ſalt upbraydings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> than any way aſſwage them with the oyl of conſolation: and that all this ſharp ſiege be laid againſt us, to pluck us from our allegeance to Chriſt, and to cut us off from being members of his body; wee muſt willingly baniſh all the but cobweb comforts of this life, to hold on the rock of comfort <hi>Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> with the diſciples, we muſt forſake our nets to follow him; with the Patriarch <hi>Joſeph,</hi> leave our garments behind us and fly away, rather than yeeld to any
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:169921:34"/> ſinfull pleaſure which ſhould ſeparate us from him; yea, deveſting our ſelves of all our wealth, fly away naked, with the yong-man in the goſpell, rather than abandon our ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue which ſhould apparrell our minds. In which loſſe of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, there is this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, that it is a great allay unto the devills temptations; for as a Serpent (ſaith <hi>Pliny</hi>) ſhuns a naked man, but purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a clothed; ſo the devill doth not ſo eaſily aſſayl a poor man with temptations, who with the poſſeſſion, hath alſo laid aſide the affection of temporall things: but he hath a great advantage of prevayling over the rich; as the Apoſtle ſaith: <hi>They that will be rich,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.9.</note> 
                     <hi>fall into temptation, and a ſnar of the devill, and into many unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:169921:34"/> and hurtfull luſts, which drown men in ruin and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi> Wee muſt therefore part with the fruit of our bodyes, to preſerve us from the ſin of our ſouls; and rank our friends, health, wife, yea life and all, in the number of trifles; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how infinitly they are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballanced by the proper worth of Chriſt, as alſo by the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit which reflects upon us from him,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.2.</note> 
                     <hi>who is the author and finiſher of our faith: who for the joy that was ſet before him, endured the Croſſe, and deſpiſed the ſhame, and ſitteth at the right hand of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Very many are the examples of heathen men, who for ſome privat good unto themſelves, as the attainment of learning; or ſome publique good unto their Country, as the ſafety
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169921:35"/> thereof, have willingly ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred up themſelves to divers forms of outward calamity. <hi>Democritus</hi> pulled out his own eyes; <hi>Crates</hi> caſt all his goods into the ſea; <hi>Pythagoras</hi> ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed himſelf from his native ſoyl; <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> neglected all publique honours, all privat contentment, that he might let his thoughts looſe wholly to the ſtuddy of Philoſophy. <hi>Ancurus</hi> the ſon of <hi>Midas</hi> ſacrifiſed his life to the floods, <hi>Curtius</hi> to the flames, that they might fix their Countries in their former ſafety. <hi>Codrus</hi> the king of <hi>Athens,</hi> when both he and his enemies had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at the oracle of <hi>Apollo,</hi> who ſhould be conquerors, and that it was anſwered, They whoſe king ſhould fall in the battell; hence it being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamed
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:169921:35"/> through both armies, that no hands fury ſhould direct it ſelf againſt the king of the contrary ſide; <hi>Codrus</hi> to delude the policy of his adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, ſhrowded under the habit of a common ſouldier, ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led himſelf in the battell, and there with over-daring valour, provoked death to ſeiſe upon him, and ſo preſerved as many by his valiant death, as he had done by his juſt life. And ſhall thoſe heathen perform all theſe things, for the gaining or keeping of ſome ſuch thing, as can but in the ſecond file chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge a place in our affections; and ſhall not wee doe and ſuffer more, to hold Chriſt in our hearts by faith and love? with whom the availes of the whole world being counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyſed, prove too light; as he
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:169921:36"/> himſelf teſtifieth ſaying; <hi>What doth it profit a man,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 16.26.</note> 
                     <hi>if he win the whole word, and loſe his own ſoul?</hi> But above all, match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe herein have been the examples of holy Martyrs and Saints in all ages of the Church, whoſe unſpeakable ſufferings for the love of Chriſt, and rather than they would beleeve, or doe, or ſo much as think a thought which was not war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by his word, were ſuch, that though they could not win pitty to their ſuffering, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief to their aſſertions, yet by their patience and courage in ſuffering, they taught the higheſt degree of admiration to the hardeſt conceipts. Let then theſe great letters in the Chriſt-croſſe-row, make up a book for us, which running wee may read, and coppy out their
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:169921:36"/> actions for our lives imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>But alas, how farr are moſt men in theſe dayes ſtrayed from the Serpentine prudence of our forefathers, in their care of preſerving their head <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> unaſſayled or at leaſt unhurt? but rather, like <hi>Judas,</hi> who ſold him for thirty pence, many of us are ready to ſell him thirty times for a penny. The cruelty of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> was piety compared to us; that which the moſt of them did, was as S. <hi>Paul</hi> confeſſeth of himſelf,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.6.</note> 
                     <hi>ignorantly through unbeleef;</hi> but wee profeſſe wee know him, profeſſe wee beleeve in him, and yet <hi>crucifie again to our ſelves the Son of God.</hi> When thou contemneſt or neglecteſt the Ordinances of God, thou ſpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt in thy Saviours face; when
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:169921:37"/> thou diſobeyeſt the juſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of thy ſuperiours, thou platteſt a crown of thornes on his head; when thy hands are hands of iniquity, and thy feet are ſwift to ſhed blood, thou naileſt his hands and his feet; when thou op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeſt, or doſt not relieve the poor, thou giveſt him gall and vinegar to drink; when thou doſt, or conſenteſt to any thing which endomageth his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, his Servants, thou cryeſt out with the Jewes, <hi>crucify him, crucify him. Qui in deum delinquit, eum relinquit: Hee that ſins againſt God, forſakes him.</hi> Whoſoever purchaſeth any profit, enjoyeth any plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, giveth way unto any Paſſion, ſatisfieth himſelf in any action which Gods word hath pronounced unlawfull, it
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169921:37"/> is he, that contrary to the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſerpent, hazards the loſſe of his head, putteth himſelf in danger to be ſeparated from Chriſt to preſerve his hands or his feet, his hayr or his nayles, or any thing that is of lower valew; and is like unto the <hi>Jewes,</hi> who cryed out, <hi>not him, but</hi> Barabbas.</p>
                  <p>Such are all covetous perſons, whoſe greedy affections are like <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> lean kin, which when they had eaten up the fat, it could not be perceived that they had eaten it; but were ſtill as evill-favoured as they were before: ſo theſe men, whatſoever they devour, are never ſatisfied, but have their deſires as vaſt and empty as ever; and are like Apprentiſes Chriſt-maſſe-boxes, to take all in, but to reſtore none till they be
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:169921:38"/> broken, nor they till they bee dead. Such are alſo the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers of bribes, who like <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hazi,</hi> when they receive a bribe, believe they receive a Bleſſing, for ſo he called it; but as he found it, ſo ſhall they, that a bitter Curſe is couched under it: for whatſoever men get by bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, ſacrilege, oppreſſion, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fury, coſenage, forſwearing, lying or the like, is like to prove as fatall to them, as that peece of fleſh which the Eagle ſtole from the altar, that had a coal clave to it, which ſet her neſt on fire. Such alſo are all thoſe who doe ſpend their means as unlawfully as theſe get it; who as S. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith, when the poor members of Chriſt are pinched with hunger and want, doe profuſely ſpend their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates on harlots, on drink, on
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:169921:38"/> dice, on balls, on plays, on vain and ſoul-killing pleaſures: or elſe their time in idleneſs, and impertinent viſits; like one <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> on whom was made this Epitaph:
<q>Here lyes <hi>Vatia,</hi> who grew old in nothing but idleneſs.</q> Or elſe in vain, obſcene, foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, fruitleſs diſcourſes, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larding their ſpeeches with lies, to make them more plauſible; powdring them with oaths, to make them (as they think) more gracefull. O what a folly is it in thoſe men (and in whom almoſt is not that folly?) that when they may hold Chriſt, and the conſequent thereof their Salvation, for denying of themſelves unlawfull gains or pleaſures, ſuch as periſh like <hi>Jonas gourd,</hi> as ſoon as they be ſprung up, and leave nothing
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:169921:39"/> behind them but repentance; when they may keep the true faith and love of Chriſt with the loſs of their lives, by which loſs they ſhall gain it; of their honours, of their eſtates, of their friends, for which they ſhall be recompenced, even in this life, an hundred fold; will yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, with <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> for the politique reſpect of kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of his kingdom; with <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> for the declining of ſome bodily danger; with <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> for with-holding back a little money; with <hi>Saul,</hi> for preſerving the fatteſt of the Cattle; with the man of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for the unchaſt em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces of a harlot; with <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tazar,</hi> for c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rowſing in the cups of the Sanctuary; yea with our firſt Parents, for an apple, or a piece of bread, as
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:169921:39"/> 
                     <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, will tranſgreſs, and ſuffer themſelves to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from the fountain of life, <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> rather than ſay with holy <hi>Joſeph,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 39.</note> 
                     <hi>How can I doe this evill, and ſin againſt my God?</hi> O let not, let not the leaſt ſhadow of ſuch weakneſs fall upon our ſouls, as ſhall make us prefer any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our union with Chriſt, but let us (as we ought) witneſs the truth of the Apoſtles, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our ſelves;<note place="margin">Mat. 19.27.</note> 
                     <hi>We have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken all, and followed thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now that which muſt knit and glue us unto Chriſt is faith; which while we hold, <hi>we ſhall be able to quench all the fiery darts,</hi> the temptations of the devill, as ſaith the Apoſtle. The devill and his inſtruments the wicked, while they rob us of our externall felicities, doe but
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:169921:40"/> as <hi>David</hi> did unto <hi>Saul,</hi> cut off the lap of our garments; but if they force us from the fortreſs of our faith, as he did unto <hi>Goliah,</hi> they cut off our heads. Let us therefore keep faith and a good conſcience, and make no ſhipwrack of that precious merchandize, like <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by S. <hi>Paul:</hi> but in all the rough tempeſts of this lifes ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, let us anchor our faith and hope upon Chriſt, who is the ſure ground of our ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. In all the <hi>Syren</hi> enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſinfull pleaſures, with <hi>Ulyſſes,</hi> let us tie our ſelves to the main-maſt of a ſtrong, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable, godly reſolution; whereby whatſoever evill wee ſuffer, or ſeeming good we may enjoy to rent us from the ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſs of our faith, we may
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:169921:40"/> ever with ſuch a calm, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant indifferency give them en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, that neither the one nor the other may remove us: but that we may ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main like a man in an open field, who to which part of the horizon ſoever he ſends his eye, he himſelf is alwaies in the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And let us not like the dirty-minded <hi>Gadarens,</hi> baniſh Chriſt out of our Country, for the loſs of a few ſwine; nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake our profeſſion of him, nor ſwerve one hayrs bredth from the line of his Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to inherit whatſoever ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther profit, or pleaſure, or ought elſe hath endeared to the eye of the world: ſeeing their purchaſe is care, their poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion trouble, their eſſence va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and their end miſery. But rather in the midſt of this
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:169921:41"/> worlds conflicts, let us engrave that triumphant motto of S. <hi>Paul</hi> on the Enſign of our Faith;<note place="margin">Rom. 8.35.</note> 
                     <hi>Who ſhall ſeparate us from the love of Chriſt? ſhall tribulation, or anguiſh, or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, or nakedneſs, or perill, or perſecution, or ſword? I am certain that neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities, nor Powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor ſtrength, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God, which is in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus our Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:169921:41"/>
                  <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
                  <p>A Fourth excerciſe of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the Serpent, not unworthy our imitation, is this: The Serpent when hee ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, to avoid the danger of drowning, keepeth his head alwaies lifted above the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: So wee while wee ſwim through the Sea of this lives actions, muſt ever bear up the head of our reaſon, that we be not drowned in pleaſure and delight. The world is a Sea, and man a ſhip; adverſity is his ballaſt, proſperity his ſayls, paſſions his Saylors, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon his Pilot, who ſits at the helm to ſteer his courſe aright: adverſity like ballaſt keeps us even and ſteddy; but when our over-buſie paſſions doe hoyſe
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:169921:42"/> up more ſayls of pleaſure, than our weak barks can bear, we run our ſelves under water, and over-whelm our reaſon, and reaſonable ſouls in the dead Sea of ſin.</p>
                  <p>Of the two grand enemies of the ſoul, proſperity and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, this is more horrid in the view, but that more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous in the event. A Summers Sun-ſhine, is the mother of more diſeaſes, than a Winters Froſt. The one ſeeketh to make a conqueſt on our vertue by force, and that makes us (like a beſieged City) fortifie our ſelves more ſtrongly for reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; the other, by the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of peace, by the tribute of gifts, ſeeks to bring our minds into ſervitude, and this melts our ſouls, our too too eaſie ſouls into yeelding. The fire
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:169921:42"/> burns hotter by being blown on by the cold wind, but the Sun ſhining on it, well nigh puts it out: ſo vertue flames more brightly, being blown on by the cold wind of adverſity, but is extinguiſhed by the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of proſperity; like lime, which is ſet on fire with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and (as they ſay) is quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with oyl. That proſperity doth draw more to ruin, than adverſity doth drive, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>David</hi> doth intimate; where he ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 9.7.</note> 
                     <hi>a thouſand ſhall fall beſides thee, and ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand at thy right hand:</hi> There is ten to one, whoſe vertue the right hand of proſperity doth choak more than the left hand of adverſity doth ſtarve.</p>
                  <p>Yet this is not the legitimate iſſue of proſperity, but a ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard; not the neceſſary effect
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:169921:43"/> thereof, but ſuch a one, as unto which, our abuſe thereof gives birth. For God gives proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity and delights unto us, as he gave <hi>Manna</hi> to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to nouriſh and refreſh our elſe-fainting ſouls, whilſt wee travail through the ſtony and thorny wilderneſs of this worlds troubles and incumbrances: but it is our abuſe of it beyond his preſcription, which begets this evill effect; as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> keeping their <hi>Manna</hi> longer than was commanded, it tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into Worms. As S. <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> ſaith, <hi>non eſt cenſus in cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, ſed affectus: there is no evill in proſperity it ſelf, but in our over-love of it;</hi> which Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-like, turns the ſweetneſs of it to poyſon in our ſelves. As it happened in <hi>Solomon,</hi> who
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:169921:43"/> abuſed the unparalleld riches and glory of his kingdom, unto the love of ſtrange women, and ſtrange Gods; which brought forth this effect alſo, even the renting of the greateſt part of the kingdom from his ſucceſſors.</p>
                  <p>Pleaſure like a Snayl, which creepeth from the bottome to the top of the tree, ſtealeth upon all, but chiefly on the higheſt; where it deſtroyeth the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of vertue, as that devours the leaves; leaving nothing behind but a ſlimie tract of foul and infamous example. Of which we muſt therefore taſte very ſparingly, as <hi>Jonathan</hi> did hony, only with the top of his rod; for as hony eaten abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly breeds much choler, ſo does the abundant ſweetneſs of pleaſure, the bitterneſs of Gods wrath. The Dogs that drink
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:169921:44"/> at the river <hi>Nilus,</hi> doe but take a lap and away, for fear the <hi>Crocodiles</hi> ſhould come and devour them; wee ſhould but ſip of the water of earthly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, leſt by our dwelling thereon, we offer our ſouls a prey unto the devill. Pleaſure is of a bewitching and alluring nature, which advantage the devill taketh againſt us, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertly hiding ſome dangerous temptation under ſuch a fair-ſeeming outſide. <hi>Hanibal,</hi> to entrap his enemies, mingled their wine with Mandrake, whoſe operation is betwixt ſleep and poyſon; ſo the devill with the wine of proſperity doth mingle the temptation of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, which while we over-greedily ſuck in, wee caſt our ſelves into the drowſie Lethargie of ſin.</p>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:169921:44"/>
                  <p>It is reported of a certain beautifull woman, that had ſo long accuſtomed her ſelf to poyſons, by making them her ordinary food, that ſhe brought her whole conſtitution and complexion to be of the ſame power that the poyſon was, and yet ſhe retained ſo much outward ſweetneſſe, that ſhe allured kings to her embraces; even ſo proſperity and pleaſure hath ſo long pampered it ſelf with the poyſon of ſin, that her nature is almoſt become in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious; and yet doth ſhe provoke moſt men to her love, by retaining an outward beauty and colour of being the ſame ſhe was. It behooveth us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to beware of her enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and not be won by the ſweetneſſe thereof, to forſake our right unto the kingdom of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:169921:45"/> heaven; nor to ſet up our reſt here in this world, like the two tribes and a half, who by the pleaſantneſs of the land were perſwaded to dwell on this ſide Jordan, and not to enter into the land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> Which that we may doe we muſt (wiſely imitating the Serpent) keep our heads above the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that is, not ſuffer our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be infatuated with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, nor drenched in the rivers of delight. But let us ſo bear her up, that ſhe may bear us up; for while a man keeps his head above water, his head will keep him from drowning. And let our reaſon direct us in the due meaſure of pleaſures that we ought to take; which holding the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of phyſick and not of food, if we take too deep a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:169921:45"/> draught thereof, it may deſtroy us.</p>
                  <p>But it is a miſery which deſerves a further degree of ſorrow than tears can expreſſe, to behold with what unſtinted appetite men in theſe dayes (eſpecially thoſe whom the bountifull hand of God hath crowned with plenty) doe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue their pleaſures; as if they were born to no other end, but to live, and to waſt that life in voluptuouſnes: and whereas we ſhould take moderat plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures only to refreſh us in the troubles of this life, they deſire life only to enjoy their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: ſo that it hath gained the place and credit of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb amongſt us, to ſay, <hi>what's a gentleman but his pleaſure?</hi> And what's their pleaſure, but the pleaſure of ſin? who abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:169921:46"/> the bounty of God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he hath beſtowed upon them the riches of this world, and their pretious time, doe ſpend them in ſuch unlawfull actions, as would ſtartle an honeſt mans heart to think, and ſurprize him with horror to declare. Whoſe impious demeanour doth far ſurpaſſe the wits and inventions of all libellers, in doing more wickedneſſe, than they could imagine; and conquering the examples of all paſt ages with their tranſcendent impieties. In whom drunkenneſſe, and gluttony, pride, vanity, and luxury, have loſt the name of vices by their frequent uſe, and have purchaſed the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of being a man's warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table manners: ſo that not to be evill, is now counted the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:169921:46"/> greateſt evill, and to be ſo, the greateſt vertue;<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.4.</note> in ſo much as (as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith) <hi>they wonder that you doe not run together with them, into the ſame confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of luxury, ſpeaking evill of you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Seneca ſaith, <hi>the time ſhall come wherein drunkenneſſe ſhall be honored, and it ſhall be count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a vertue to drink ſtoutly.</hi> That time came long ſince, and ſtill remaines; wherein many are ſo buried in ſleep and wine that that may be veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of them, which was once ſpoken of the Emperor <hi>Bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, Non ut vivat natus eſt, ſed ut bibat; He is not born to live, but to drink;</hi> who being after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſtrangled with a halter, was thus jeaſted at by the People; <hi>amphora pendet non homo: it is a pitcher that is
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:169921:47"/> hang'd and not a man.</hi> And in this delight doe men drown the head of their reaſon, and darken the eyes of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and ſo like blind men, fall from hence into the depth of all other impieties. With <hi>Noah,</hi> they diſcover the nakedneſſe of their diſpoſitions to the deriſion of every beholder; &amp; are ready in they drunkenneſs, with <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, to kill their deareſt friends; with <hi>Marcus Antonius,</hi> to vomit on the Tribunall; with <hi>Lot,</hi> to defile their own daughters: yea what beaſtly evill is there amongſt thoſe, which nature herſelf ſhames to behold, to which this vice opens not a way? St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> reports of a certain young man, who being drunk, raviſhed his mother, Stabd his Father, and wounded
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:169921:47"/> two of his ſiſters to death. And therefore the Poets ſay, that <hi>Bacchus</hi> the Heatheniſh God of wine, was born in thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and is uſually painted with horns, becauſe that drunkards are alwayes puſhing and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling, and their effects dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and dreadfull. And no leſſe dangerous are the effects of gluttony, though not ſo common, becauſe more coſtly; and yet too too common: for doe we not ſee, that although heatheniſm be baniſhed, yet Idolatry is ſtill maintained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us; and men having no other Idol, doe idolize them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and make that dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill covered with ſnow, their bellies, their God; whoſe altars, their tables, they make to crack with the weighty Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of their delicious viands:
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:169921:48"/> they impoveriſh ſea and land to enrich their tables, and tenter their inventions with unheard-of dainties, to pleaſe the witty gluttony of a meal. What hewing and ſquaring is there of their bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y-timber, their diet? while their ſouls in the mean time (as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeaketh) <hi>are daubed up with untempered morter.</hi> What coſt is there? what curioſity, in deſpite of nature, to preſerve things beyond, or to haſten them before the time that ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hath allotted for their ſeaſon? And for the better reliſh of theſe their cates, they wiſh (with <hi>Philox<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nus</hi>) their necks as long as a cranes, that they may feel the more ſweetneſſe in their meats and drinks. <hi>Meates for the belly, and the belly for meats</hi> (ſaith <hi>St. Paul)
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:169921:48"/> but God ſhall deſtroy both it and them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To this doe men add the exceſſe of over-coftly apparrell and perfumes, of ſumptuous buildings, and rich furniture, of revellings and dancings, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimes and ſports; conſuming therein more than would main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain an army; wearing the price of a Lordſhip at their eates, yea at their ſhooes, with <hi>Pop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pea</hi> the wife of <hi>Nero.</hi> They out vie the bravery of the Lillies, as much as they did <hi>Solomons,</hi> and ſtrive to outſhine the Stars in the number and luſter of their pretious Stones; diſdaining to let their feet touch that earth, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lſt they live, which their heads ſhall be covered with, when they are dead: whoſe glory, like a flaming palace, while it ſhines
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:169921:49"/> conſumes them, and in the end will bring them to aſhes. <hi>Lucius Plotius,</hi> who was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the Triumvirate, and <hi>Muleaſſes</hi> the expulſed King of <hi>Tunis,</hi> were bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayl the unhappy exceſſe of coſtly perfumes, who hiding themſelves for fear, were betrayed to their enemies by the ſmell of their ſweet odors. And in theſe and the like kinds of exceſſes, doe men drown both their reaſon and their fortunes, both their ſouls and bodyes; and are not only paſſive, but active in their own ruine; they doe not only ſtand under a falling houſe, but pull it down upon them; and are not only executed, which implyes guiltineſſe; but they are executioners, which implyes diſhonour; and executioners
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:169921:49"/> of themſelves, which implyes impiety. And when in theſe prodigious impieties men have melted their patrimonies, they are forced to continue their profuſeneſſe by injuſtice, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, coſenage, and all kinds both of craft and cruelty; like birds and beaſts of prey, ſatisfying their own ravenous deſires with the ruins of others; and making one ſin the fuell to another; with thoſe ſhames of nature, and monſters of mankind, <hi>Nero, Caligula, Domitian,</hi> and many others. But above all, the example of <hi>Cleopes</hi> a king of <hi>Egypt</hi> is moſt remarkable in this kind, who wanting money to finiſh the witneſſe of his folly begun in the building of a <hi>Pyramis,</hi> and being barren of all other means, baſely proſtituted the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:169921:50"/> body of his moſt beautifull daughter, to every ſlave that would bring one ſtone ready poliſhed to the building there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And although there are but few King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erours, or perſons ſo vaſtly rich, as to make themſelves guilty of ſuch monſtrous impieties<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> according to the uttermoſt extention thereof; yet in the intention and vehemency of their deſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es (as their practice, according to their ability doth ſhew) there are too many: who are the pictures of <hi>Sardanapalus,</hi> and <hi>Nero</hi> in miniature<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and their contents bound up in a ſmaller volume.</p>
                  <p>And no leſſe then the moſt frequent of the former evills, doth unlawfull Luſt tyrannize amongſt men, who conſume therein their bodyes and goods,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:169921:50"/> their good names and their ſouls: which is ſuch a ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full nature<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that it doth fly the naming, of ſuch fearfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences that they exceed the naming. Who is there that (with holy <hi>Job</hi>) hath made a covenant with his eyes, not to look upon a woman to luſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her? and is not rather like unto <hi>Dinah</hi> the daughter of <hi>Jacob,</hi> who went a gadding to ſee the maids of the Country, untill ſhe was none her ſelf? By whom the Stews are more boldly frequented than the Church, or at leaſt more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly;<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.14.</note> 
                     <hi>having eyes full of adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery</hi> (as ſaith S. <hi>Peter) and that cannot ceaſe to ſin.</hi> Such is the heat of their unlawfull deſires, that it cannot hide it ſelf in their hearts but muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eep out at their eyes, which like bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-glaſſes,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:169921:51"/> collect the beams of beauty, which ſet their hearts on fire: on whom the law of <hi>Zaleucus</hi> of <hi>Locris</hi> were deſervedly executed, who commanded that the eyes of the adulterer ſhould be pulled out. Luſt is an infernall fire, whoſe fuell is gluttony and drunkenneſs, whoſe ſparks are obſcene words, whoſe aſhes are uncleanneſs, whoſe ſmoke is infamy, and whoſe end is torment. And in theſe and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more voluptuous courſes, doe millions of men ruin their ſouls; into whom, as into the herd of Swine, the devils doe enter, and carry them head-long into the deep of eternall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
                  <p>I deny not but there is a lawfull uſe of all Gods crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; he made (as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:169921:51"/> ſaith) Oyl to make a man have a cheerfull countenance, and wine and bread to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, mans heart; and there is a place allowed to ſilks, and gold, and pretious ſtones, both for our uſe and ornament; to each one according to his abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and dignity. They that are in Kings Courts, may wear ſoft rayment; but it was the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the rich glutton in the Goſpell, to be clothed in purple and fine linnen, and to fare deliciouſly every day: and it was the brand of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that they ſat down to eat and to drink, and roſe up to play. We may have theſe things, but they muſt not have us; their uſe muſt follow our reaſon, not tread it down; we may ſometimes ſwim in lawfull pleaſures, but we muſt
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:169921:52"/> never be drowned in them. But when our pleaſure in theſe earthly things doth exceed the due meaſure, or our delights direct themſelves unto unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full objects; yea, when we doe not only abuſe our delights but delight in that abuſe; when we doe not only commit evill, but rejoyce in evill committed; flattering and hugging our ſelves in our abhorred courſes, like impious <hi>Nero</hi> that laughed at the flame of that great City that himſelf had ſet on fire, yea when men proceed to ſuch an height of w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ckedneſs (and to ſuch a he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ght they doe proceed) that though they make the devil and his fiends glad, yet they make them wonder more, to ſee that man of himſelf is grown more exquiſite in evill, than their temptations can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:169921:52"/> them, and make them wiſh their wickedneſs were their own: then our Reaſon, and Piety<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and all good forſakes us; and we juſtly pull upon our ſelves that curſe of the <hi>Pſalmiſt;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſ. 68.23.</note> 
                     <hi>Let their table be made a Snare unto them, a recompence, and a ſtumbling block; Let their eys be darkned, that they may not ſee, and alwaies bow down their backs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>God indeed made Woman for man, <hi>Eve</hi> for <hi>Adam;</hi> yet he never ſaid <hi>encreaſe and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply,</hi> untill they were married; to ſhew that he hath a curſe, and not a bleſſing for unlawfull unions. He alloweth us the uſe of meats and drinks, but wee muſt take them <hi>ſeaſonably</hi> as, <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>for ſtrength,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ecc. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.17.</note> 
                     <hi>and not for luxury. Heraclitus</hi> the Philoſopher, being reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:169921:53"/> in a Sedition to declare his opinion, how the City might be brought to live in peace and concord; aſſoon as he was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended the Pulpit, called for a cup of cold water, wherein he ſtrewed a little meale, and when he had drunk it off he deſcended without ſpeak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng a word; but ſignifying thereby, after his dark manner, that ſo the City ſhould be without ſedition, if they would forſake their ſuperfluous pleaſures, and inure themſelves, to temperance and hardneſs: ſo alſo ſhall we allay the rebellion of paſſions, which lead us on to the looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of pleaſure, raiſed againſt the Soveraignty of reaſon, if we apply a mean and modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all our delights. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the ſame proportion in the dedicating of our ſelves, our
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:169921:53"/> time and means unto Gods ſervice, and our own lawfull pleaſures, (for unto unlawfull not an atome is to be allowed) that <hi>Noah</hi> did in receiving the beaſts into the ark; of which there were ſeven couple of clean to but two of unclean; ſhewing us thereby, that as the ſeven clean couple were for the ſervice of God, and the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary ſuſtenance of man; and the two unclean only for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and recreation ſo our time and means ſpent in world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſures, ſhould bee much leſs than that which we offer to the ſervice of God, and our own neceſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ies. And as Hunters will not ſuffer their hounds to eat much carrion when they are to hunt becauſe the ſtrength thereof offends the quickneſs of their ſent, and hinders the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:169921:54"/> purſute of their game; ſo ſhould we forbear to glut our ſelves with carrion-pleaſures, which doe ſo infect our minds, that they deprive us of delight in goodneſs, and hinder us from proſecuting our devotions to God, and our endeavours in our callings. And though men enjoy the pleaſures of ſin, yet they will laſt but for a ſeaſon, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith; and then, as <hi>Saturne</hi> by whom the antients did ſignifie pleaſure, who was therefore ſo called, <hi>à Saturan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, of glutting,</hi> as <hi>Iſodore</hi> ſaith, was alwaies painted moſt ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull; ſo the ſhort line of their pleaſures will end in the period of ſadneſs and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: as <hi>Boetius</hi> ſaith, <hi>volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates triſtes habent exitus,</hi> the pleaſures of ſin have bitter ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers through delicious ſprings:
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:169921:54"/> and as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.19.</note> 
                     <hi>whoſe end is deſtruction, whoſe belly is their God, and glory their ſhame, who mind earthly things.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let us therefore (as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour commands us) <hi>take heed that our hearts be not oppreſt with ſurfetting and drunkenneſs,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke 21.34.</note> 
                     <hi>nor with the cares nor pleaſures of this life.</hi> And as the Apoſtle ſaith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Dearly beloved,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.11.</note> 
                     <hi>I beſeech you as pilgrims and ſtrangers, abſtain from fleſhly deſires, which fight againſt the ſoul.</hi> That ſo contenting our ſelves with that moderate proportion of the Manna of pleaſure, which God hath allowed us while wee travail through the wilderneſs of this world, we may at the length poſſeſs the land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> wherein all plenty of pleaſures are perpetually reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: where our deſires ſhall
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:169921:55"/> never want ſatisfaction, nor ſatisfaction ever breed ſatiety: where we ſhall enjoy the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py fellowſhip of Saints and Angels, and the moſt bleſſed viſion of God himſelf;<note place="margin">Pſ. 15.11.</note> 
                     <hi>in whoſe preſence is fulneſs of joy, and at whoſe right hand are pleaſures for evermore.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:169921:55"/>
                  <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
                  <p>THE laſt work of Prudence to which the ſerpents ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample doth invite us, is this that followeth. It was the cuſtome of thoſe places where ſerpents did moſt abound, to draw them out of their lurking holes with charmes, and ſo deſtroy them; as the Poet ſaith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Frigidus in pratis cantando rumpitur anguis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The cold Serpent in the meadows is burſt with charme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now the Serpent to prevent this danger, doth ſtop his eares; as the Pſalmiſt ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 57.6.</note> 
                     <hi>like the deaf adder, which ſtoppeth her eares, which will not hear the voice of the charmers, and of the ſorcerer enchanting wiſely.</hi>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:169921:56"/> Which ſhee doth (as S. <hi>Jſodore</hi> ſaith) by laying one eare cloſe unto the ground, and ſtopping the other eare with her tayle: So ought wee to reſiſt the charmes, that is, the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of that grand Magicke the devill, with his compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the fleſh and the world, by the conſideration of the end, ſignified by the ſerpents tayl; and with the memory of the worlds vanity, frailty, and inconſtancy, as ſhee doth by laying the other eare unto the ground.</p>
                  <p>The brittle frailty of this world, and of the vanities thereof, unto whoſe fruition the devills temptations doe ſo importunatly urge our minds, is as certainly known to all, as it is ſeldome ſeriouſly thought on by any. For if it were, how
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:169921:56"/> can wee imagine, that men would be ſo indulgent to their crimes, and ſo obedient to the devills ſuggeſtions, that a chime doth not more cloſely follow the ſtroke of the clock, than their practiſes his provocations; as if the devill had granted them a perpetuity of pleaſure, and ſealed the monopoly of ſin to them, and to their heirs for ever. When as (alas) God ſhall quickly take their delights from them, or them from their delights: their delights from them, for as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Riches will take the wings of an eagle,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pro. 23.5.</note> 
                     <hi>and will fly into heaven;</hi> or them from their delights, as our Saviour ſaith. <hi>Thou fool, this night they take away thy ſoul.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke. 12.20.</note> 
                     <hi>Moyſes</hi> well remembred how ſhort liv'd they were like unto that flower
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:169921:57"/> which <hi>Pliny</hi> ſpeaks of which ſprings in the morning, is full blown at noon, and fades at night;<note place="margin">Heb. 11.25.</note> and therefore <hi>choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bee afflicted with the children of God, than to enjoy the temporall pleaſure of Sin: counting the reproach of Chriſt greater riches, than the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Egiptians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The world for the frailty and inconſtancy thereof, is by S. <hi>John</hi> compared to a ſea; as he ſaith in the <hi>Apocalips; Before the thron there was a ſea of glaſſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Apoc. 4.6.</note> 
                     <hi>like unto cryſtall;</hi> by which ſea is meant the world, which for it's frailty is glaſſe, for it's unconſtancy a ſea. A ſea ſwelling with pride, blew with envie, boyling with anger, deep with averiſe, frothy with luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. It is a Sea, tempeſtuous with controverſies, ſtormy with
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:169921:57"/> affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctions, tumultuous with diſorders. The ſea yealds an obedient conformity to the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the moon, and ſwels higheſt in a joyfull imitation, when ſhee is in the ſpring-tide of her light, either towards the heavens, as in the change, or towards the earth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as in the full; and as ſhee doth wax or wain, ſo doth he either flow into a pleuriſy, or ebbe into a conſumption of his waters: and even thus is the world the page of fortune, whoſe uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and ever-changing moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, doe hurry about, like ſpokes in a wheel, the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all mortalls: as the Apoſtle ſaith;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.31.</note> 
                     <hi>The faſhion of this world paſſeth away.</hi> An hour-glaſſe doth change it's poſture every hour, and that part which was even now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:169921:58"/> is now below; that which was even now full, is now empty; nor can one ſide be filled, but by emptying the other; ſuch is the world, every moment turn'd upſide down, and men are now full, now empty; Nor can they often fill themſelves, without the ruin or prejudice of others, yea ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times, as <hi>Laban</hi> did to <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acob,</hi> when men have toyled in it's ſervice many years, it rewards them with loathed <hi>Leah,</hi> inſteed of loved <hi>Rachel.</hi> Like <hi>Jael</hi> it carrieth milk in one hand to nouriſh, and a hammer and a nayl in the other to deſtroy; and as <hi>Joab</hi> did to <hi>Amaſa,</hi> while it kiſſeth us, it killeth us. And although like the moon, it be ſometimes at at the full of glory yet is it even then like her alſo mingled with
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:169921:58"/> the ſpots of adverſity, and ſubject to the change of every moment. And therefore (as they ſay) at the conſecration of the Popes, the Maſter of the ceremonies goeing before, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth in one hand a burning ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, in the other a ſtick with ſome flax tyed on the top there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which he ſetting on fire, cryeth with a lowd voyce, <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſancte, ſic tranſit gloria mundi; Holy Father, ſo paſſeth away the glory of the world.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The plenty of hiſtories in this kind exceedeth our Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metique; every particular mans condition, almoſt being a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume of the worlds frailty, and a conſtant witneſſe of it's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy. <hi>Adonibezec</hi> in the firſt of the book of <hi>Judges,</hi> who had been the triumph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Victor over ſeventy Kings,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:169921:59"/> and in his wanton cruelty cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the thumbs of their hands and feet, made them pick up crums under his table; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcing the act, yet depriving them of the power, making them doe that which hee had diſabled them to doe, was ere long returned with an equall meaſure, which made him cry out;<note place="margin">Judg. 1.7.</note> 
                     <hi>As I have done, ſo God hath rewarded me. Nabucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donozor's</hi> unparallel'd <hi>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſis,</hi> who knoweth not? Who in the deſpite of Philoſophy, prov'd in himſelf the tranſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gration of Species, and from a man fell into a beaſt, in nature now, as was in practiſe before; to ſhew that when men ſinne againſt the light of nature, they may ſuffer againſt the law of nature.</p>
                  <p>It is reported of <hi>Demetrius,</hi>
                     <pb n="111" facs="tcp:169921:59"/> one of <hi>Alexander</hi> the great his Captains, that in the whole cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of his life, being threeſcore years and four, after the meaſure of his age had ſtil'd him man, never continued three years in one condition. Of <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> alſo, that great awer of the world, and tyrant over the Common-wealth, it is doubted, whether in the whole courſe of his life. Fortune were an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent arbitrer unto him of good and evill ſucceſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but in the miſery of his death, no doubt all his lives happineſſe was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly overballanc'd; who in the Zenith, and higheſt erecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his glory with three and twenty wounds, the deepeſt whereof given by his deareſt <hi>Brutus,</hi> and that in the Court of his deadly enemy <hi>Pompey,</hi> yeelded up his life a ſacrifice to the peoples liberty.</p>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:169921:60"/>
                  <p>The like unhappy change purſued the ever-renowned, and once highly advanced Captain <hi>Beliſarius;</hi> who after he had triumphed over the <hi>Perſians,</hi> and reduced to the Roman obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience all <hi>Africa</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> which had been long poſſeſſed by the <hi>Gothes</hi> and <hi>Vandalls;</hi> and after he had brought one of the Kings of the <hi>Vandalls</hi> to ſuch a paſſe, that hee begged three things; a loaf of bread a ſpunge to wipe his eyes, and a harp to tune his ſorrow to; his wife who was given him for a help, became the only help to his deſtruction; whoſe inſolent behaviour againſt the Empreſſe, like winds thrown upon the Seas, raiſed ſuch billows of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation in the Emperour, that they put this good mans fortune to an utter ſhipwrack; who did
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:169921:60"/> not only loſe all his goods, but the means wherby he might get more, his ſight; and was forced to beg his bread with <hi>Da obolo Beliſario Viator,</hi> and thus, though blind did moſt cleerly ſee, the frailty of this worlds felicity. Therefore <hi>Dioniſius</hi> the King of <hi>Syracuſa,</hi> repreſented the brittle felicity of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome unto his Paraſite <hi>Damo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> (which <hi>Damocles</hi> had made to ſeem exceeding great, through the multiplying glaſſe of his flattery, by ſeating him in a royall throne, at a ſumptuous Banquet, with all the ſtate and glory of the kingdome about him; but withall cauſing a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſword to be hung over his head, which was only held up by a horſes hair, which every minute threatned his deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It was likewiſe the cuſtome
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:169921:61"/> of the <hi>Romans</hi> in their tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs, for a ſlave to ride behind in the Chariot with the trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, who did often whiſper unto him to look behind him: there was likewiſe a whip and a bell tyed to the Charyot, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh him, that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the preſent exaltation of his honour, he might be brought to ſuch a degree of calamity as to be ſcourged or put to death; of which the bell was the ſigne, it being the cuſtome of the old <hi>Romans,</hi> to ring a bell before a dead Corps, leſt any by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching too neer ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file themſelves thereby. Now if we would allow theſe and the like images of the worlds frailty a place in our conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and remember that all the glory, beauty, and pleaſures thereof, are as truly ſhort as
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:169921:61"/> they are ſeeming ſweet, and that though they bee ſweet in the enjoying yet they are bitter in the end; ſurely it would ſo ſteel our reſolutions againſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils temptations, it would ſo ſtop our ears againſt the voyce of his charms, that fear ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at the dore of our hearts, would reſiſt the entrance of ſin into our ſouls: and teach us to apply ſuch a mean and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration to all worldly endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, that as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>wee ſhould uſe this world as though we us'd it not.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.31.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The latter means wherby we muſt make deaf our ears, to the powerfull charms of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils temptations, is the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of our own end; like the Serpent, which ſtops her other ear with her tayl Which meditation may juſtly claim
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:169921:62"/> the exerciſe of our moſt ſerious thoughts, ſince the devils ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions are chiefly plotted for the undermining of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration; Who is therefore likened to a Serpent, which biteth the horſes heels, that he maketh him caſt his rider: mans body is this horſe his ſoul the rider, his heel his end; the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation whereof, if the devill doe bereave us, we are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown both horſe and man. There is no ſtronger bit to curb the temptations of our unbrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led fleſh, than to conſider what a dear price we ſhall pay for our pleaſures in our death, and at our judgement. <hi>In all thy works, remember the laſt things,</hi> (ſaith the wiſe-man) <hi>and thou ſhalt never ſin.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.40.</note> The birds direct their paſſage through the ayr with their tayls, ſo doe the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:169921:62"/> in the Sea; the rudders, motion guideth the Ship and the beaſts with their tayls beat away the flyes: temptations are flyes, whence the Devill is called <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies <hi>the God or Father of flyes;</hi> all which are repelled by the mediation of our end ſignified by the Serpents tayl; and the courſe of our actions for which we embarque our ſelves, thereby as by a rudder rightly ſteered to the Port of happineſs. When the devill tempteth us to pride, our fleſh to luſt, the world to vain delights, if we did but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low this meditation of our end a full place in our thoughts, that we muſt die one day, we may dye this day, and that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death commeth judgment, wherein we muſt ſatisfie to the uttermoſt farthing the great
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:169921:63"/> debt of our ſins, and that in ſuch a manner and meaſure, as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eloquence nor ſilence can expreſs; ſurely I think we ſhould not (as many doe) run on in evil faſter than the devill can drive them, and dare him to preſent them with a temptation which they dare not execute: but rather like the Peacock, who when he looks upon the blackneſs of his feet, lets fall his Plumes, and forgets the beauty of his train; So wee caſting our thoughts down upon our end ſhould neglect all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights that temptations promiſe in their ſinfull ſatisfaction. Every man when he is upon his bed of ſickneſs; when hee is counting his laſt ſand; when death is ſo neer him that hee cannot turn his eyes from it, every one ſeeing it in his eyes;
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:169921:63"/> then how many vows and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes doth he offer up of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting all temp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation unto ſin, unto which he hath formerly too eaſily conſented if he may but by the return of his health, renew again the almoſt expired league betwixt his body and his ſoul. Yea even the devill himſelf as the old d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ich hath it when he wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſick would be a Monk and a holy man.</p>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Aegrotat Daemon, Monachus</l>
                        <l>tunc eſſe vol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>bat</l>
                        <l>Convaluit Daemon, Daemon ut</l>
                        <l>ante fuit.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The Devill was ſick, the Devill</l>
                        <l>a Monk would be,</l>
                        <l>The Devill was well, the Devill</l>
                        <l>a Monk was he.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
                  <p>But if we did in our healths
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:169921:64"/> entertain this conſideration of death, and the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and make it as familiar and preſent to our minds, as the approaches thereof are neer unto the ſick, no doubt but it would work in us the ſame never fayling effects.</p>
                  <p>If wee did make remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, our <hi>Philips</hi> boy, to ring the knell of mortality each morning in our ears; and if with S. <hi>Jerome,</hi> there were no action of our life, in whoſe performance we did not think wee heard the ſound of the Archangels trumpet, procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming this convocation in our ears: <hi>Ariſe ye dead, and come to judgement:</hi> if we did remember theſe tormenting flames which God hath prepared for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill and wicked men;<note place="margin">Iſay 30.33.</note> 
                     <hi>whoſe fuell is fire and much wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d, the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:169921:64"/> breath of our Lord like a tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of brimſtone enflaming it;</hi> which though it torment them, yet it ſhall not conſume them, as though they ſhould have a period of their pains; but like the <hi>Salamander</hi> they ſhall live ſtill in the flame; and be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed, with <hi>Dives,</hi> a drop of water, more than their tears; which will be ſo far from aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaging their heat, that the ſaltneſs thereof ſhall encreaſe their ames: and yet in the high boyling of this their heat, ſuch conflicts of puniſhment ſhall meet in them, that through extream cold, they ſhall gnaſh their teeth; for as our Saviour ſaith, <hi>there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> If I ſay, theſe meditations were in us and did abound, ſurely, they would ſtrengthen us to ſtrangle temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:169921:65"/> in their conception, and to reſiſt the untimely birth of ſin.</p>
                  <p>If the rich man mentioned in the Goſpell, had thought that his ſoul ſhould have been hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried that night to hell he would never have dream'd of building his barns bigger. Few men will ſteel at the gallows, or ſpeak treaſon on the rack; but it is our putting the evill day far from us, that makes every day evill to us. We forget the evill of puniſhment, which make us commit the evil of ſin. Wher wee may prevent our ſins by remembring of the puniſhment then we think not on it; and when we think on it, which is not til we feel it then it is to late to prevent it. O how humbly (think you) would the <hi>fallen Angels</hi> behave themſelves, if
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:169921:65"/> they were enthroniz'd in their antient glory! O how abſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miouſly would our <hi>firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> have walked by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit, if they might have been repoſſeſſed of their earthly Paradice! And how tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly would <hi>Dives</hi> have uſed the pleaſures of this life, if hee might have been redeemed from hels tormenting flames! Let us then be as carefull not to fall into their evils, as they would bee if they were riſen out of them: which care, the meditation thereof will mainly ſtrengthen; as the oyl of <hi>Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions</hi> doth heal their ſting; that while death and hell are in us by remembrance, we may never be in them by ſufferance. For as 'tis ſaid, if the <hi>Baſilisk</hi> ſee a man firſt, it kils him; but if a man ſee that firſt, he kils it: So
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:169921:66"/> if death ſee and apprehend us firſt, being unprepared, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys us; but if we ſee it firſt, by meditation and preparation, we kill it, and become the death of death, and may juſtly take up that joyfull acclamation of S. <hi>Paul;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.55.</note> 
                     <hi>O death where is thy victory? O death where is thy ſting.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yet all muſt dye: For deaths meditation though it take away the ſting of death, yet it takes not away the body of death. But here's the difference; that death which is the wicked mans ſhipwrack, is the good mans harbour; where ſtriking ſayl, and caſting anchor, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns his lading with advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to the owner; that is, his ſoul fraught with good works unto God: leaving his bulk ſtill mored in the haven, which is
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:169921:66"/> but unrig'd to be new built again, and fitted for an eternall voyage. And as that earth in which the men of <hi>China</hi> doe bury their clay, after a hundred years doth render it purified, and refined, and fit out of it to form their choyſeſt diſhes; ſo our graves, after many years, ſhall reſtore us again, glorified, and immortalized, and fitted veſſels for the houſe of God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:169921:67"/>
               <head>Of the ſimplicitie of the <hi>Dove.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Serpent is the wiſeſt amongſt the Beaſts of the field, and is therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded as the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of our imitation, in the vertue of wiſdome; ſo the <hi>Dove</hi> doth farre leave behind her, the examples of all the brute crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the practiſe of ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And therefore the Holy Ghoſt, who is the love of the Father, which love is the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Simplicity deigned above others, in the exhibition of his teſtimony of Chriſt, to inveſt
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:169921:67"/> his Deitie with the form of a <hi>Dove.</hi> Whoſe harmleſſe ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, on which our imitation muſt attend diſcovers it ſelf (as <hi>Pliny</hi> ſaith) in theſe particulars. Firſt, ſhe hurts nothing with her clawes. Secondly, ſhe hurts nothing with her bill. Thirdly, ſhe wants a gall. Fourthly, ſhe nouriſheth, and bringeth up both her own, and others young ones. Now, theſe ſeverall pieces of the <hi>Doves</hi> ſimplicity do teach us, that as ſhe hurts nothing with her clawes, no more ſhould we throw any evill upon others by our hands or actions. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, as ſhe hurts nothing with her bill, no more ought we to prejudice any by our words. Thirdly, in that ſhee wants a gall, it forbids us to give birth unto a thought, which ſhall direct it ſelf againſt the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:169921:68"/> good of our neighbour. The firſt noteth unto us the ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our works; the ſecond of our words; the third of our thoughts. Fourthly, in that ſhe nouriſheth others young-ones, we are directed not only to doe no evill, but alſo to doe good, and that not to our own alone, but alſo to our neighbours; yea, though they be our Enemies. Theſe are the particulars, which ſhall bound this brief diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
                  <p>All works are intimated by the hands, as the principall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of working; and therefore <hi>Pilat</hi> when he would aſſoyle himſelf of that impious act of Chriſts condemnation, waſhed his hands: And the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſaith;<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſal. 25.6</note> 
                     <hi>I will waſh my hands among the innocent.</hi> Therefore did the <hi>Phariſees</hi>
                     <pb n="129" facs="tcp:169921:68"/> wear the Commandements written about their hands, to intimate their performance. Now they who are altogether barren in good works, are like unto <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> whoſe right hand was dryed up. And they who interline their good works with bad, are not unlike <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> builders, who held a trowell in one hand to build, and a ſword in the other to deſtroy One evill action amongſt many good ones, corrupts the vertues of all the reſt; like <hi>Pharaohs</hi> lean kine, that did eat up the fat: or the <hi>Colloquintida</hi> in the young Prophets broth, which made them cry out; <hi>O thou man of God, death is in thy pot.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">4 King. 4.40.</note> And not only to doe no wrong but even to doe no hurt, though lawfull, is very ſutable to the <hi>Doves Simplicity.</hi> Our Saviour who
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:169921:69"/> gave us this precept, gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf alſo for an example, who amongſt all his miracles enrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Sacred writ, never did any that tended to deſtruction, but only in curſing the barren figg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree.</p>
                  <p>S. <hi>Aug.</hi> ſaith; <hi>all juſtice is comprehended in this word inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence; all injuſtice reprehended.</hi> To the injuſtice of the hands or deeds, is referred generally all actions that ſtrike at the body or goods of our neighbour. God ſaith by <hi>Moyſes;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exod. 22.21, 22.</note> 
                     <hi>Thou ſhalt doe no injurie to a ſtranger, neither oppreſſe him; ye ſhall not hurt the widdow nor father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe child.</hi> More particularly, to the injuſtice of Magiſtrates, of Lawyers, and publick officers; who corrupted through hope, fear, hatred, or love; hope of preferment, fear of mens power,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:169921:69"/> hatred of their perſons, or love ſometimes to their perſons, but moſt times to their mony, have renewed the antient copies of injuſtice, yea and augmented them: Pleaders tongues being like the tongue of a ballance, their hands the ſcales, into one of which if you put one pound, into the other two, the tongue will alwaies incline to that which is the heavieſt. Who is there that in the generall execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the place of Magiſtracy, or the particular deſignation to the deciſion of a controverſie, in the giving of voyces in matters of Election, or in their choyce unto places of dignity which reſt in their particular power, ſwerveth not from the rule of juſtice, and ſimplicity? meaſuring the merit of the perſon, not the quantity of the gift, or relation
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:169921:70"/> of kindred or acquaintance: Like <hi>Titus Manlius,</hi> who in a caſe of juſtice gave Sentence againſt his own Son. O no, <hi>Themyſtocles</hi> ſaying pleaſeth them better, who being reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted to bear himſelf indifferently in his cenſure, anſwered; <hi>Be it far from me not to pleaſure my friends in all things.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Princes Courts doe ſwarm with their flattering dependents, who either bridled with the fear of their diſpleaſure, or ſpurred on with the hope of preferment, doe bind themſelves with the ſale of the liberty, innocency, and ſimplicity of their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to run the ſame courſe with them, in avowing all their enterprizes, in obeying all their commands: like <hi>Pilat,</hi> who leſt he ſhould ſtrike againſt the rock of <hi>Caeſars</hi> offence, condemned
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:169921:70"/> the innocent Lamb of God unto death; and <hi>Judas,</hi> who betrayed him for a piece of money.</p>
                  <p>The example of <hi>Martinus</hi> a Cardinall is very memorable; who travelling on his way, one of his horſes fell lame, which the Biſhop of <hi>Florence</hi> ſupplied with the free gift of another: which Biſhop afterwards com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to <hi>Rome,</hi> craved the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage of the Cardinall in a cauſe of his; to whom he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, firſt let me redeem my liberty, and gave him another horſe, and now (ſaith he) if your cauſe be juſt I am your Patron. I would this were the practiſe of all the Clergy; and that of <hi>Philoxenus</hi> of all Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers; who (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> reports) being demanded of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the King of <hi>Syracuſa,</hi> what he thought of certain verſes of his,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:169921:71"/> anſwered (according to his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) that they were naught, whereat the King diſpleaſed condemned him to digge in the Quarry-pitts; but by the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of friends being reſtored <hi>Dionyſius</hi> demanded again what he thought of other verſes of his; but he knowing that they were naught and remembring his late puniſhment, anſwered not a word, but called to one of the Guard, to carry him again to the Quarry-pitts. And he that will not with <hi>Phyloxenus,</hi> rather ſuffer evill then doe it, may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly receive the juſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Syamnes</hi> a certain Judge; who as <hi>Herodotus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, being corrupted by money to give wrong Sentence, King <hi>Cambyſes</hi> cauſed his skin to be pulled off, and nayled to the Tribunall; that they that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:169921:71"/> terrified by his example, might avoyd his wickedneſſe.</p>
                  <p>Juſtice amongſt the Antients was ſuppoſed to be a Virgin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe ought alwaies to be pure, ſimple, and uncorrupt. And ſurely their wiſdomes fail them, who think that their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, injuſtice, and injurious handling of others, can raiſe them to the true pitch of Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; ſeeing that like <hi>Jonathan,</hi> and his armour-bearer, who clymed up to the top of a rock on their hands and feet they rear themſelves hereunto by grovel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, baſe and ſordid means: For the truth of greatneſſe reſts not in the height of worldly wealth, or honour, but of juſtice and ſimplicity. And therefore <hi>Agiſelaus</hi> obſerving the <hi>Aſians</hi> uſually to crown their King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> with the title of <hi>Great;
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:169921:72"/> wherein</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is he greater than I, unleſſe he be wiſer or juſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now as the ſimplicity com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended unto us, is likened to the Doves; ſo many of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vices, have their reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance in the nature of other birds. There is the deſperate Cock, the contentious man, whoſe injurious quarrellings make good the motto of <hi>Iſhma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> in himſelf,<note place="margin">Gen. 16.12.</note> 
                     <hi>His hand againſt every man, and every mans hand againſt him.</hi> There is the Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock, the proud man, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who thought themſelves graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoppers in compariſon of the Giants of <hi>Canaan,</hi> he thinks himſelf a giant in worth and excellency, and all others but graſhoppers in compariſon of himſelf; when indeed he is but
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:169921:72"/> a ſwoln impoſtume, caſting out rotten and loathſome matter, in his words and actions. There is the Cuccow that layes her eggs in the neſts of other birds; the cloſe adulterer, whoſe children ſit at other mens fire, and eat at other mens tables. There is the Swan that ſings ſweetly, yet devours his own kind; ſuch are flatterers and hypocrites, who as our Saviour ſaith,<note place="margin">Math. 23.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Praying long prayers devour widdowes houſes.</hi> There is the Swallow, that ſtaies with us in the Summer, but flyes away in the Winter; ſuch are falſe friends, who abide with us in our proſperity, and with it depart; ſhewing that they were friends to it, and not to us. There is the Cormorant, the covetous man, who ſpares not to grind the faces of the poor, to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the hire of the labourer, to
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:169921:73"/> coſen the fatherleſſe and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, yea any man; yea God himſelf, by robbing of the Church, and with holding things conſecrated with wicked <hi>Achan.</hi> Who when they have ranſacked the bowels of the earth for treaſure, are forced through their fears to hide them there again; like the Adders young, who being newly come out of their damms bellie, run thither again for ſafety, if af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted with any danger. There is alſo the Vulture that follows armies to prey upon dead car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſſes; the griping Uſurer, who waits upon prodigall heirs to devour their decaying fortune; unto whom whoſoever ſeeks for ſuccour, is like unto a ſheep which in a ſtorm runs under a bramble for ſhelter, where he is ſure to leave part of his fleece
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:169921:73"/> behind him. Theſe, and the like, are the practiſes of thoſe, who are not, as they ought to be, innocent and ſimple as Doves.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                  <p>THe ſecond part of our <hi>Dove</hi>-like ſimplicity, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in our not prejudicing any in our words, as ſhe hurts nothing with her bill. <hi>S. Paul</hi>'s command is,<note place="margin">Tit. 3.2.</note> 
                     <hi>to ſpeak evill of no man;</hi> which S. <hi>James</hi> knew to be ſo difficult, that he ſaith;<note place="margin">James 3.2</note> 
                     <hi>If any man offend not in word, that ſame is a perfect man, and able alſo to bridle the whole body. Nabals</hi> churliſhneſſe, <hi>Shemey's</hi> rayling the childrens mocking the infirmity of the Prophet <hi>Elizeus,</hi> deriſions and upbray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:169921:74"/> miſconſtruction of our neighbours actions, the divul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the faults of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, falſe accuſations againſt them, and detracting from their juſt merit, theſe are words, which (as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith) <hi>are like the prickings of a ſword;</hi> yet theſe are the unworthy and cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry exerciſes of our tongues, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſuch as are not unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with <hi>the language of Canaan.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Epiſt. Judae. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Michael the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angel, when diſputing with the devill, he contended about the body of Moyſes, durſt not rayle againſt him, but ſayd, our Lord repreſſe thee; but theſe men ſpeak evill of things they know not,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Jude;</hi> and by their raſh and precipate judgement of other mens actions, their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtructions, and interpreting to the evill part, let blood the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:169921:74"/> good name of their brethren, even to the fainting, yea death of their dear credit; and many times in the effect thereof, to the deſtruction of their lives. Thus delt the devill with <hi>Job,</hi> the Children of <hi>Ammon</hi> with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> with our Saviour. Impoſſible it is for a man ſo evenly to deport himſelf, that his actions can eſcape the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt conſtruction of fame-woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding tongues: ſuch were the <hi>Phariſees</hi> in their cenſure of Chriſt, and S. <hi>John Baptiſt; Math.</hi> 11.18. <hi>John came nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eating nor drinking, and they ſay he hath a Devill: the Son of man came eating and drinking, and they ſay, behold a glutton, and a drinker of wine, a friend of Publicans and ſinners.</hi> Theſe are the moſt direct An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipodes to the ſimplicity of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:169921:75"/> words; who, when they cannot find faults, doe make them; and like corrupt ſtomacks, turn all the good meat they eat into corruption.</p>
                  <p>Little leſs are they that wound the fame of their neighbours in tale-bearing by revealing of their ſins, and ſlidings: like impious <hi>Cham,</hi> who diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and derided the drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his father <hi>Noah;</hi> for which hee was juſtly curſed. And by every ones adding ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to in their reports, making it like a Snow-ball, which, the further it rowls, the more it gathers. And in the mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of mens worth by detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting from it, or allaying it with infamous aſperſions; thinking by diſparaging others, to give the greater luſtre to their own commendations; and to raiſe
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:169921:75"/> their own on the ruins of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans good name. Calu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mniation is the infallible note, not only of an unchriſtian, but alſo of an ignoble diſpoſition; and ſurely they are conſcious to themſelves of their own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs, who need the foyl of another mans fault, to ſet off their own vertue. <hi>Hecuba</hi> when ſhee was with child of <hi>Paris,</hi> dream'd that ſhe was brought to bed of a fire-brand; and ſuch indeed he afterwards proved: So theſe men deliver themſelves of that foul-mouth'd monſter detraction, whoſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous effects are able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame the world with mutuall diſcords. As S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith; <hi>There is a detractor, who ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth but a word, and yet that word in a moment doth poyſon the ears, and wound the hearts
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:169921:76"/> of the hearers.</hi> Whoſe ſting like that of the venemous <hi>Taran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tula,</hi> bred in the kingdom o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Naples,</hi> which is not to to be cured but by muſick, can find no remedy but the melody of a ſincere and patient mind; prepared to indure whatſoever it can inflict, yet able to ſpunge out whatſoever it can object.</p>
                  <p>The name of Devill in the Greek (from whence it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived) ſignifieth a Calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; and calumny and detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction (with all its kindred) are devilliſh ſins; whereby men goe about like him, <hi>ſeeking whom they may devour:</hi> prying and liſtning after the demeanour of other men, obſcuring and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuating their good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the news of their evils with joy, and reporting and augmenting them with uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:169921:76"/> cruelty, and falſhood. In which caſe, King <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> his practice, is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy our ſtricteſt imitation, who was wont to ſay, That he was much beholding to the <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> for that they ſpeaking evill of him, were a great cauſe of making him a good man; for ſaith he, I doe daily enforce my ſelf, both by word and deed, to prove them lyars.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iſmaels</hi> deriding his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Iſaack,</hi> is called in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture a perſecution and though they were but Children that mocked the Prophet <hi>Elizeus,</hi> calling him bald-head, yet God ſeverely puniſhed them, by ſending two Bears amongſt them; which deſtroyed two and forty. To reproach any, with either their naturall, or accidentall infirmities, is a note
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:169921:77"/> of pride and inſolence; whereby men triumph over others, and are inwardly tickled with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in themſelves, while they conceive themſelves free from thoſe things, they object againſt others. But as they deal with their brethren, ſo God will deal with them; who as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Will ſcorn the ſcorners, and give grace to the meek.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Some there are indeed who ſpeak fair and praiſe much, but it is but to deceive and hurt; like the Spider that weaveth a curious web out of her own mouth to catch poor flyes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled in her ſnare: and ſo they differ not in the end, but in the way of doing evill; like <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> Foxes, who though their headsſtood contrary ways, yet they were tyed together by the tayls. And this is more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:169921:77"/> to ſimplicity than the reſt of the vices of the tongue; for ſimplicity ſignifies freedome from folds and doublings, (<hi>Simplex, quaſi ſine plicis,</hi> ſay the Grammarians;) but in ſuch deceitfull words, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but doubleneſs. <hi>Judas</hi> his <hi>nayl maſter,</hi> his kiſs and treaſon; <hi>Jaacobs</hi> voice, and <hi>Eſau's</hi> hands ſuit not well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it is like the practice of the <hi>Panther,</hi> who by the ſweetneſs of his breath inticeth paſſengers to draw near him and when they are come within his reach, devours them: ſo doth a deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man by fair words and ſhews of friendſhip, invite men to truſt him, and then deceives them. Againſt this practice, the Prophet <hi>David</hi> doth moſt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly exclaim, ſaying,<note place="margin">Pſal. 54.13.</note> 
                     <hi>If mine enemy had reproached me, I
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:169921:78"/> could have born it; and if he that hated me, had ſpoken great things againſt me, I could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps have hid my ſelf from him; but it was thou that wert of mine own mind, my guide, and my acquaintance, who did eat plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant meat together with me; wee walked with conſent in the houſe of God:</hi> then follows; <hi>Let death come upon them, and let them goe down quick into hell; for wickedneſſe is in their dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and in the middeſt of them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I find nothing more frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nor more vehemently repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in Scripture than the abuſe of the tongue: from whence we may gather, both the frequency and hainouſneſſe of the fault; which is intimated by the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, where he ſaith, <hi>The ſons of men, their teeth are weapons
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:169921:78"/> and darts, and their tongue a ſharp ſword.</hi> And again,<note place="margin">Pſal. 57.5</note> 
                     <hi>They have whetted their tongues like a ſword, they have bent their bow,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">63.4.</note> 
                     <hi>a bitter thing, that they might ſhoot ſecretly at the ſpotleſſe.</hi> And therefore he prayeth;<note place="margin">119. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Deliver my ſoul, O Lord, from unjuſt lips, and from a deceitfull tongue,</hi> S. <hi>Jerome</hi> alſo affirmeth the ſame, ſaying, <hi>So great an itch towards this evill hath invaded the minds of men, that they that have forſaken all other vices, doe yet (as it were into a forreign ſnare) fall into this.</hi> Therefore as he counſelleth; <hi>Never ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniate, or detract from any one, and ſtudy rather to adorn your own life, than carp at an others.</hi> And remember the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made by the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 33.14.</note> 
                     <hi>What man is he that deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth life, and longeth to ſee good
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:169921:79"/> dayes? reſtrain thy tongue from evill, and thy lips that they ſpeak no guile.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. III.</head>
                  <p>THe third part of our priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Simplicity, conſiſteth in the meekneſſe and unconque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rableneſſe of the heart by anger, hatred, envy, deſire of revenge, and the like; wherein we imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the ſimplicity of the Dove, in wanting of a gall. Againſt wrath; hatred, and all ill will, the Church doth teach us to pray, and the Dove to practice: <hi>Whoſoever is angry with his brother,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 5.22.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhall be guilty of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> ſaith our Saviour; and, <hi>he that hateth him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.15.</note> 
                     <hi>is a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlayer,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Iohn.</hi> And
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:169921:79"/> S. <hi>Iames, If you have bitter en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and ſtrife in your hearts,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jam. 3.14.</note> 
                     <hi>boaſt not.</hi> Can they then be ſimple as Doves, whoſe fiery ſpirits, like the flint, are no ſooner ſtruck againſt the ſteel of a hard and contumelious word, but preſently they ſparkle fire in the eyes of him that ſtrook it? O no, for as the Apoſtle ſaith;<note place="margin">Jam. 1.20.</note> 
                     <hi>The wrath of man doth not work the juſtice of</hi> God. Yea, ſome there are whoſe leaſt thwart in their deſire doth boyl up their blood to ſuch a height, and heat of fury, that nothing but the cold haud of death can quench or allay it: as it is reported of <hi>Mathias</hi> King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> who ſitting one day at dinner, accompanied with Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours from the King of <hi>France,</hi> called for Figs; and receiving anſwer, that there were none,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:169921:80"/> immediatly fell into ſuch a rage, that it drove him into an Apoplexie, who never ſpake word after, but as if his Soul had been angry with his own body alſo, forſook it the next day, and dyed. And therefore ſurely it was wittily feigned of the Poets, that <hi>Prometheus</hi> lacking clay to finiſh his man, was forced to patch it up with parts taken from ſundry beaſts; and amongſt the reſt, did put the heart of a furious Lion into the breſt of man.</p>
                  <p>Or can he be ſimple as the Dove, whoſe env<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ous heart with-holds his eyes from look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aright upon any happy man? whoſe ears can bear the burden of no mans praiſe; who contrary to the nature of all other plagues, is plagued with others well being; making hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:169921:80"/> the ground of his unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe and good news the cauſe of his ſorrow; whoſe favour none can win but by being mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable: like Porpiſes, which play and rejoyce in a ſtorm, but are ſtruck with a ſilent ſadneſſe in fair weather. <hi>Cain</hi> envied the acceptation of his brother <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel; Rachel</hi> the fruitfulneſſe of her ſiſter <hi>Leah;</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> the ſucceſſe of his ſervant <hi>David;</hi> And it is reported of <hi>Themiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> that all ſleep was baniſht from his eyes, through his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme envy at the glory of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiades.</hi> Thus doth the envious heart work upon it ſelf with inbred ſtings like the mountain <hi>Aetna,</hi> which conſumes its own bowels with inward bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings.</p>
                  <p>Or can they have any inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in this Dove-like ſimplicity,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:169921:81"/> who for ſome ſmall and private injury, yea many times for the truth (for that is often the mother of hatred) do proſecute each other with ſuch deadly cruelty, and ſuch blood-thirſty revenge, as neither friendſhip, kindred, nor Religion can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, nor the long tract of mens lives can wear out? Thus did the private hatred betwixt <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey,</hi> pull down ruine on the Roman Empire. Thus <hi>Arius</hi> diſdaining at his repulſe in aſpyring to a Biſhoprick, broacht ſuch an hereſie as over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread the whole Chriſtian world; yea death it ſelf on the one party, in ſome, cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the hatred of the ſurvivor: witneſſe the Story of <hi>Pope Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> the ſixt, who cauſed the body of his Predeceſſor <hi>Formo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> to be taken up, and beheaded
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:169921:81"/> in the market place, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards caſt into <hi>Tyber.</hi> Yea death in both parties, which hath killed the men, yet hath not kild their malice; if the ſtory of <hi>Eteocles</hi> and <hi>Polynices</hi> be true which ſaith, that when they had by mutuall wounds, made windows for each others ſoul to fly out at, their bodies being burnt together, their very flames divided themſelves, as hating to be united in their dead bodies, who were ſo divided in their living affections.</p>
                  <p>Thus <hi>homo homini Lupus, one man is a Wolf unto another;</hi> in whoſe hearts, and hands, and mouths are the inſtruments of miſchief; as the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 13.3.</note> 
                     <hi>Their throat is an open Sepulcher, they delt deceitfully with their tongues, the poyſon of Aſpes is under their lips:
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:169921:82"/> whoſe mouth is full of curſing and bitterneſs, their feet are ſwift to ſhed blood. Sorrow and unhappineſs is in their wayes, and the way of peace they have not known, the fear of God is not before their eyes.</hi> I have read that a ſtring made of Wolfs guts, laid amongſt a knot of ſtrings made of the guts of Sheep, corrupts and ſpoyls them all: it is a ſtrange ſecret in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſerves to inſinuate the malice of theſe <hi>Lycant hropi,</hi> theſe Wolf-turn'd men, againſt the Sheep of Chriſts flock: for which cauſe our Saviour gave us this commandement, ſaying, <hi>Behold I ſend you forth as ſheep in the midſt of Wolves, be ye therefore prudent as Serpents, and ſimple as Doves.</hi> Simple as Doves,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.9</note> 
                     <hi>not returning evill for evill, nor curſe for curſe, but on
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:169921:82"/> the contrary bleſs, becauſe you are called to this, to be heirs of bleſſing;</hi> as ſaith S. <hi>Peter.</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo ſaith;<note place="margin">Rom. 12.17.18.19.</note> 
                     <hi>Render evill for evill to no man. If it be poſſible, as much as in you is, have peace with all men. Avenge not your ſelves, but give place unto wrath, for it is written, vengeance is mine, I will repay, ſaith our Lord.</hi> And as it is reported of the wals of <hi>Bizan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium,</hi> that they were ſo ſmooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and cloſely wrought, that they ſeemed to be but one ſtone; and of the building of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> temple, that there was not ſo much as the noyſe of a ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer to bee heard therein: So ſhould wee have all our thoughts, our words, our deeds, ſo even, ſo ſmooth ſo poliſht, that they ſhould not ſend forth the leaſt noyſe of injury to our
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:169921:83"/> neighbour, or ſound of diſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
                  <p>YEt this is not enough<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to doe no evill, but we muſt alſo doe good: Chriſt curſed the fig-tree, not for any hurt it did, but becauſe it did no good, it brought forth no fruit. And this exerciſe of good, muſt not be centred in thoſe only which either prevent or return us with an equall meaſure, like the Scribes and Phariſees, the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans and ſinners; but it muſt expatiate and diffuſe it ſelf, like the impartiall Sun to all even to our enemies. And ſo we ſhall be ſimple as Doves; who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that they doe no hurt to
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:169921:83"/> any living creature, doe alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently nouriſh both their own, and others young ones. Now this practice of good, muſt receive its form from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer prohibitions of evill; to wit, in thought, word and deed.</p>
                  <p>Firſt then in thought, wee muſt have our hearts ſuppled, and entendred with charity, meekneſs, gentleneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> humility, and patience. It was the greateſt commendation of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> that he was ſtiled,<note place="margin">Num. 12.3.</note> 
                     <hi>the meekeſt man upon earth:</hi> for which cauſe God converſed with him more familiarly than ever he did with any, as the Scripture ſaith,<note place="margin">Exod. 33.11.</note> 
                     <hi>God talked with him face to face, as a man talketh to his friend:</hi> and our Saviour ſaith;<note place="margin">Math. 11.29.</note> 
                     <hi>Learn of me, for I am meek and lowly in heart, and ye ſhall find reſt unto
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:169921:84"/> your ſouls.</hi> The valleys are more fruitfull than the mountains, and the weightieſt ears of corn bow down their heads the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt towards the ground; ſuch are the riches of humility, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing men like figures in arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metique, where the laſt in place is greateſt in accompt. Our charity likewiſe expecteth of us, that we ſhould breath forth nothing but deſires of bliſs unto our brethren; not ſuſpecting evill without great ground; not beleeving evill without ſtrong proof;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.5.</note> for <hi>charity thinketh no evill;</hi> as ſaith the Apoſtle. And God hath propounded himſelf for an example unto us, to prevent our too eaſy ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up upon truſt, a prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall report againſt our brethren, in the eighteenth of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> where he ſaith ſpeaking of
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:169921:84"/> 
                     <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha</hi> thoſe wicked Cities,<note place="margin">Gen. 18.21.</note> 
                     <hi>I will goe down and ſee whether they have done according to the cry that is come up unto me, and if not ſo that I may know:</hi> not as if God were ignorant of the truth of any thing, but for our inſtruction it is thus written, to teach us (as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith) that <hi>wee ſhould not apply our hearts to all words that are ſpoken;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.22.</note> nor by too haſty beleef, doe that, which muſt be undone again.</p>
                  <p>Our patience likewiſe, in which our Saviour comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth us <hi>to poſſeſs our ſouls,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke 21.19.</note> claimeth of us an unreſiſting ſufferance of evill; though there be whole vollies of injuries diſcharged againſt us, yet muſt our hearts be in ury-proof, and our patience preſerve us un-hurt, unprovoked to anger, hatred,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:169921:85"/> deſire of revenge, and their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous effects; for as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.10.</note> 
                     <hi>anger reſteth in the boſome of a fool.</hi> And although the Apoſtle bids us <hi>be angry and ſin not,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.26.</note> yet it is but a permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, not a command; and I ſuppoſe, it is eaſier not to be angry at all, than to be angry and not ſin at all. For anger in mans breſt is like fire in an Oven, which if it be quite damd up, is extinguiſhed; but having but a little vent, is apt to rage too fiercely. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.32.</note> 
                     <hi>Be ye courteous one to another, and mercifull, forgivi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>g one another, even as God for Chriſts ſake forgave you.</hi> Yea ſo far muſt our patience in injuries, and our charitable return to thoſe that have injured us proceed, that we muſt not only cancell
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:169921:85"/> the debt of all their injuries, ſo that not ſo much, as in a thought may we wiſh them any evill, as it is evill; but alſo, if any adverſe accident doe befall them, wee muſt be inwardly moved with a compaſſionate ſorrow for the ſame. As <hi>Job</hi> declaring his own innocence, teſtifieth of himſelf;<note place="margin">Job 31.29</note> 
                     <hi>If I have rejoyced in the ruin of him that hated me, or have exulted that evill found him out.</hi> And the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſaith, ſpeaking of his enemies, <hi>I mourned for him, as for mine own Mothers ſon.</hi> And thus ſhall we truly imitate the Dove<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who inſtead of ſinging doth alwaies mourn; and wee ſhall alwaies have cauſe to doe ſo, if we conſider both the ſpirituall, and corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall evils of our neighbours, throughout the world. To
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:169921:86"/> render evill for evill, is human frailtie; to render evill for good, is deviliſh impiety; to render good for evill is god like puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: in which practice if wee inſiſt, we ſhall approach neer unto the pattern of the holy Ghoſt, and to that which above all other creatures doth beſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe his nature, the Doves; and ſo we ſhall be ſimple as Doves.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. V.</head>
                  <p>SEcondly, to maintain the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of our words, they muſt take upon them a mild, a gentle and charitable form; we muſt apparell our thoughts in the ſoft rayment of meek and well-filed ſpeech, and dreſſe our
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:169921:86"/> words in the ſupple accents of love of modeſty, of courteſie, of truth. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to <hi>Titus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Tit. 3.2.</note> 
                     <hi>Put them in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, that they be modeſt, ſhewing all meek<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſſe unto all men.</hi> It was the ſaying of <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> the Emperour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that no man ought to depart from the preſence of a Prince diſpleaſed, ſuch ſhould be the gratiouſneſſe of his words and anſwers; and ſuch ſhould be the practice of every Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith again,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 4.6</note> 
                     <hi>Let your ſpeech be alwayes gratious, ſeaſoned with ſalt, that you may know how you ought to give an anſwer to every one.</hi> And in the ſudden over-ſights of our brethren committed either in word or deed without unſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſcoffing or deriſion mildly to overpaſſe them, not being
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:169921:87"/> cruell in anothers faults; for as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith; <hi>It is the glory of a man to paſſe by unjuſt things.</hi> And to give the moſt gentle and favourable interpretation of all mens actions without the ſeverity of a raſh and bitter cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.5</note> as the Apoſtle ſaith; <hi>Iudge not before the time.</hi> And if the certain notice of any evill acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our neighbour come to our knowledge, like <hi>Noahs</hi> two Sons, <hi>Sem</hi> and <hi>Japhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> we muſt cover the nakedneſſe thereof with the mantle of ſilence; go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing backward as they did that if it were poſſible, we m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ght hide it even from our own eies; for what S. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ter</hi> ſaid of love,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.8.</note> is true alſo of Simplicity, which is the effect of love that <hi>it cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a multitude of ſinnes.</hi> And let us ſay that ſurely the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of ſome ſtrong temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:169921:87"/> drove him into it, into which we our ſelves may fall if that the eſpeciall grace of God doe not ſupport us.</p>
                  <p>Nor is this practice to be ſtinted only to thoſe who wear the name of friends, but it muſt be extended even to our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; as the Apoſtle ſaith of the duty of ſervants to their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, <hi>Not only to the good and courteous, but alſo to the fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> If therefore we ſhould be invaded by ſcoffing <hi>Iſhmaels,</hi> or rayling <hi>Shemeyes,</hi> or receive any other unjuſt uſage, we muſt not, (like the dog that bites the ſtone, but regards not the hand that threw it) turn again to tender rebuke for rebuke, but contrariwiſe bleſſe, as the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> commandeth us: and quiet our ſelves with the conſideration of the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> who
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:169921:88"/> ſaid concerning <hi>Sheme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Kings 56.10.</note> 
                     <hi>Let him alone, that he may curſe: for our Lord hath commanded him that he ſhould curſe David.</hi> I ſpeak not here concerning Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours, either Eccleſiaſticall or Civill, who have power (no doubt) to reprove thoſe that are ſubject unto them; nor of notorious and heynous malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, ſuch as <hi>Herod,</hi> whom our Saviour called Fox; ſuch as <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> whom S. <hi>Peter</hi> in many words ſharply repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; and ſuth as the heretique <hi>Marcion,</hi> whom St. <hi>Polycarp</hi> called <hi>the eldeſt ſon of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill:</hi> for theſe no doubt deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it in a moſt eminent man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. God reproved the high Prieſt <hi>Eli,</hi> for not reproving his ſons more ſharply; yet becauſe we are almoſt all prone to bow too much on this ſide, it is good
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:169921:88"/> (like a young tree that growes ſomewhat awry) bow to our ſelves as much the other way; that ſo in time we may keep the middle. And let us remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber two examples of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in this kind; one in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the Supper, where there was found one that had not on a wedding garment, to whom, though he were a wicked man, the Maſter of the feaſt afforded a courteous compellation, ſaying, <hi>Friend,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 22.12.</note> 
                     <hi>how cameſt thou in hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi> The other concerning the woman taken in adultery, whom when he diſmiſt, it was with no worſe words than theſe, <hi>Woman,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">John 8.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>goe thy wayes and ſin no more.</hi> And ſurely, if there be any means to prevent the enraged hearts of men, from boyling our at their mouths in bitter words, or breaking out at their hands
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:169921:89"/> in hurtfull deeds, it is this; as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Prov. 15.10.</note> 
                     <hi>a ſoft anſwer breaketh wrath, a hard word raiſeth fury.</hi> Thus <hi>Abraham</hi> prevented a breach between his own, and the family of <hi>Lot,</hi> ſaying,<note place="margin">Gen. 13.8</note> 
                     <hi>Let there be no wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, I pray thee, betwixt thee and me, nor betwixt thy ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards and my ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>pheards, for we are brethren.</hi> Thus alſo ſpake <hi>Gedeon</hi> in the book of Judges, to the incenſed men of <hi>Ephraim,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Judges 8.2, 3.</note> ſaying, <hi>Is not a cluſter of grapes of Ephraim better than a vintage of Abt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>zar?</hi> And the Scripture ſaith, that <hi>when he had thus ſpoken, their ſpirits w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ted, whereby they ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt him.</hi> Even as the force of a bullet, ſpit out of the fiery entrayles of a gun, is ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered in a ſoft pack of wooll, or quenched in the yeelding wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:169921:89"/> when as encountring with a reſiſting wall it batters it to peeces.</p>
                  <p>This government and reſtraint of the tongue, is a moſt difficult leſſon in Chriſtianity, eſpecially when men are highly provoked, either by injurious words or deeds: which made S. <hi>James</hi> ſay, <hi>Every nature of beaſts,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">James 3.7, 8.</note> 
                     <hi>and birds, and creeping things, and other things, are tamed, and have been tamed by man, but the tongue no man can tame; it is an u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t evill, full of deadly poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> It is reported by <hi>Euſebius,</hi> that an unlearned man called <hi>Pamlus</hi> requeſted a friend of his to teach him a Pſalm, who when he had read unto him the firſt verſe of the 38. Pſalm, <hi>I ſaid I will keep my wayes, that I aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>d not with my tongue;</hi> would not ſuffer the next verſe
<pb n="472" facs="tcp:169921:90"/> to be read, ſaying, I will firſt learn to practiſe this: and when his teacher blamed him becauſe he had not ſeen him in ſix weeks after, he anſwered that he had not learned that verſe: and one asking him many years after, whether he had then learned it or no; I am forty years old, ſaith he, and yet I have not lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to fulfill it. Which difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (as is uſually in noble minds) ſhould ſo much the more whet our endeavours, and awaken our induſtry, that ſo in the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of our tongues, wee may arrive to the pitch of the example propounded to us, and be ſimple as Doves.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="173" facs="tcp:169921:90"/>
                  <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
                  <p>THirdly, it is not enough for us, like <hi>Dives</hi> dogs, only to lick mens ſores with our tongues, to give them good words only, but no further helps; but in our actions alſo we muſt follow all men (ſo far as in us lyeth) yea, and prevent them with our good turns; obſerving therein that order which S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſets down,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.10</note> 
                     <hi>While we have time</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>let us doe good unto all, but eſpecially to the houſhold of faith:</hi> and that time that <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> mentioneth;<note place="margin">Prov. 3.28.</note> 
                     <hi>Say not unto thy neighbour, goe and come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to morrow, and I will give thee, if thou canſt give now.</hi> We ſhould be ſo covetous of doing good, that we ſhould ſeek, nay make occaſions, rather than
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:169921:91"/> expect them; and that with a mind ſo zealous of wel-doing, that the world ſhould ſooner ceaſe to afford opportunities, than we want will to apprehend them; as S. <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifieth of the Churches of <hi>Macedonia,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.3.</note> 
                     <hi>that to their power, yea, and beyond their power, they were willing:</hi> and as <hi>Job</hi> witneſſeth of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,<note place="margin">Job 29. v. 11, 12, 15, 19.</note> 
                     <hi>I was an eye unto the blind, and a foot unto the lame; J was father of the poor, the ear that heard did bleſſe me, and the eye that ſaw gave teſtimony of me, becauſe I delivered the poor man that cryed, and the pupill that had no helper.</hi> And with good reaſon, for as St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> ſaith, <hi>it is much more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent to feed hungry Chriſt,</hi> (that is to ſay his members) <hi>than to raiſe one from the dead in the name of Chriſt; for in
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:169921:91"/> this, Chriſt deſerveth at thy hands, in that, thou deſerveſt at his; for miracles thou art Gods debtor, for mercy he is thine.</hi> And they that cannot contribute one ſort of good works for the aſſiſtance of their brethren, let them doe another; for there is ſcarce any ſo barren of power to doe good, but that in ſome<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing or other, either ſpirituall or corporall, either great or lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, he may be ſerviceable to his neighbour; as the fable well expreſſeth, which ſaith, that when the Lion was taken in a ſnare, the poor weak Mouſe gave him his help, to gnaw the cords in ſunder. We muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore like the taper, which burns it ſelf out to give light unto others, ſpend the talent that God hath given us (next unto his glory) to the benefit of our
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:169921:92"/> brethren; yea, to his glory in the benefit of our brethren, as our ſaviour ſaith; <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good works, and glorifie your father which is in heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this muſt be done, not only when we are hereunto in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited by the counter courteſies, or inoffenſive neceſſities of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; but even then when we receive from them the ſharp en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters of contrary miſchief. When we are aſſaulted with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries (in humane conſtruction) beyond the ability of ſufferance, or degree of reconcilement, we muſt ſtrike off the tally of all their injuries, and if their need require, repay them with good turns;<note place="margin">Rom. 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0.</note> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Jf thy enemy ſhall hunger, feed him; if thirſt, give him to drink:</hi>
                     <pb n="177" facs="tcp:169921:92"/> like the Patriarch <hi>Joſeph,</hi> who rewarded the mercileſſe cruelty of his brethren, by preſerving that life in them, which they would have deſtroyed in him. The law of requitall, is a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple deeply rooted in the nature of man; whereby wee deem, that if one have broken his duty unto us, by offering us an injury, we are abſolved from our duty to him, and may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the imputation of wrong, requite him with an equall injury: but we muſt know, that the duty of man unto man, is enjoyned in Scripture without condition or limitation, <hi>Do good unto all</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi>) not only if they doe good unto you (for that exceedeth not the righteouſneſſe of <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> which can never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the kingdom of heaven)
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:169921:93"/> but though they doe evill: as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith again,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.21.</note> 
                     <hi>Be not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of evill; but overcome evill with good.</hi> To yield unto our repentant enemies the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of pardon, is a degree of Charity, of which there is a ſhadow and image even in noble beaſts; for the Lion (they ſay) abateth his fierceneſs againſt any thing that doth proſtrate it ſelf unto it. To pardon our enemies perſiſting without ſatisfaction or ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, is a ſecond degree of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which is found in the ſoft and gentle natures of ſome men. But to pardon our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting enemies, yea more, to deſerve well of them by doing of them good, and that not out of a bravery or greatneſs of the mind, which delighteth in the fruit of its own vertue, but out
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:169921:93"/> of a heart appaſſionated with ſorrow for his miſery (if he be in any) and entendred with the love and deſire of his good; this is the pureſt and the higheſt exaltation of fraternall Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, this is a ſimplicity imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the divine nature, and the hardeſt leſſon in all Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
                  <p>Whoſe coppy we have pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cild out unco us in the practice of our Saviour, who, being God, and his enemies but men, did infinitly excell them in dignity, which made their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries infinite; and in power alſo, whereby he was able, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to prevent their miſchiefs, or eſcape them; yea, to ſpeak them all into nothing aſwell as his word at firſt gave them a being out of nothing; did yet notwithſtanding, with a love
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:169921:94"/> as great as their injuries were grievous, reward their reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches with his prayers; their buffetings with his balſome; their treaſons with his truth. They diſgracefully ſpit on his eyes, and he with ſpittle healed their eyes; they made the blood to iſſue out of him, and he ſtopt the iſſues of blood in them; they took away a life from him, and he reſtored life to many of them; yea that very life of his, which their cruelty ſacrificed to their revenge, did his love ſacrifice for their redemption. There was never ſorrow like unto his ſorrow, nor ever love like unto his love; both being byeyond all example, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to all for an example; which while we make haſte to imitate,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.20.</note> 
                     <hi>we ſhall upon our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:169921:94"/> heads heap coles of fire,</hi> (as the Apoſlle ſpeaketh) which ſhall either enflame them with a correſpondency of affection, as heat begetteth heat; or elſe, for their unrelenting hearts, ſhall ſerve to augment their quenchleſs flames in hell. And for our ſelves receive we our comfort, in the words of our Saviour;<note place="margin">Mat. 5.11.12.</note> 
                     <hi>Bleſſed are ye when they ſhall curſe you, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute you, and ſpeak all manner of evill againſt you falſly, for my ſake; rejoyce and be glad, for great is your reward in heaven.</hi> And thus if wee order our thoughts our words, our deeds, both negatively, by thinking, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, doing no evill; and poſitively, by thinking, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, doing good; and this, not to our own alone, but even
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:169921:95"/> to our enemies; we ſhall reach the height of the example pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to us, and be ſimple as Doves.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:169921:95"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
